<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the honorable sentence and execution of the Queene of Scots exempled with analogies, and diuerse presidents of emperors, kings, and popes: with the opinions of learned men in the point, and diuerse reasons gathered foorth out of both lawes ciuill and canon, together with the answere to certaine obiections made by the fauourites of the late Scottish Queene.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17566.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108326</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843987</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843987</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8764</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07158)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8764)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 254:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the honorable sentence and execution of the Queene of Scots exempled with analogies, and diuerse presidents of emperors, kings, and popes: with the opinions of learned men in the point, and diuerse reasons gathered foorth out of both lawes ciuill and canon, together with the answere to certaine obiections made by the fauourites of the late Scottish Queene.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn VVindet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1587]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to Maurice Kyffin.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]²  A⁴ B²  C-L⁴ ² D-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>"Anthony Babingtons letter to the Queene of Scots" (caption title) begins a section of letters on ² D1r.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Half-sheet L is in two states: L1r has (1) a lace ornament or (2) an ornament of putti playing music.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 15098 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Queen of Scots, 1542-1587 --  Death and burial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentence and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>of the Queene of Scots:</hi> EXEMPLED WITH A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogies, and diuerſe preſidents of Emperors, Kings, and Popes: <hi>With the opinions of learned men in</hi> the point, and diuerſe reaſons gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>foorth out of both Lawes</hi> Ciuill and Canon, Together with the anſwere to certaine ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections made by the fauourites of the <hi>late Scottiſh Queene.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Vlpians Maxim.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juris executio nullam habet iniuriam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The execution of Lawe, is iniurious to no man.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by Iohn Windet.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:2"/>
            <head>The contents of the booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The firſt Chapter conteining an Analogie or Reſemblance between <hi>Ione</hi> Queene of <hi>Naples,</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> late Queene of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The ſeconde chapter contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an other Analogie or Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance betweene the Emperor <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinius</hi> and the ſaid queene <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The third chapter conteining certaine preſidents of ſundry Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors &amp; kings, that haue in ſome caſe put other princes vnto death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The fourth chapter contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the actes and iudgementes of ſundrie Popes, which haue appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the death of ſome Princes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> The fift Chapter conteining a confirmation of the honorable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence &amp; execution paſt againſt the late Scottiſh Queene, by ſundrie reaſons and authorities gathered foorth of the Ciuill and Canon lawe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> The ſixt chapter conteining ſeuerall aunſweres to ſeuerall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections lately made againſt the ſaid ſentence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> The ſeuenth chapter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is prooued that in two eſpeciall caſes, the drawing of the ſworde of one Prince againſt another, is not onely lawfull, but moſt neceſsarie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> The concluſion vpon the ſum of the ſaide Chapters.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:3"/>
            <head>AN ANALOGIE OR reſemblance betweene Ione <hi>queene of Naples and Marie</hi> queene of Scotland.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>One</hi> queene of <hi>Naples</hi> being in loue vvith the duke of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collmitius lib. <hi>5.</hi> in historia Neapolitana. Petrus Mexia in vita ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>celai. Hiſtoria blondi Epitome pij ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi.</note> cauſed hir husband <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draſius</hi> (or as ſom terme him) <hi>Andreas</hi> king of <hi>Naples,</hi> (vvhom ſhe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fauoured) to be ſtrangled in the yeare of our Lord God 1348.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie</hi> Queene of Scotland being (as appeareth by the Chronicles of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande</hi> and her ovvne letters) in loue vvith the Earle <hi>Bothwell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Author. de nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs Mariae. Bucchanan. in historia rerum Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icarum.</hi> Hir casket of letters were deliuered to the Lordes out of Edingburg caſtle by lames Balford one of the conſpiracie againſt the king. See the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the doings of Mary Queen of Scots &amp;c. and the inditement of Bothwell &amp; other like printed in Scottiſh.</note> cauſed hir husband <hi>Henrie</hi> Lorde <hi>Darley</hi> king of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (vvhome ſhee made ſmall account of long time before) to be ſtrangled, and the houſe vvhere he lodged called <hi>Kirk of fielde</hi> to be blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vven vp vvith gun povvder, the tenth
<pb facs="tcp:8764:4"/>of Februarie in the yeare of our Lord God 1567.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Jone</hi> queene of <hi>Naples</hi> did preſentlie after the ſhamefull ſlaughter of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande,<note place="margin">Colinutius lib. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>216.</hi>
               </note> 
               <note place="margin">Petrus Mexia.</note> marrie vvith the ſaide Duke of <hi>Tarent,</hi> notvvithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that they vvere ioyned in kinred neere togither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie</hi> Queene of <hi>Scotlande</hi> ſhortly after the villanous death of her ſayde husband,<note place="margin">Author de nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs Mariae. Buconan fol. <hi>190 191.</hi> lib. rerum ſcoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> vvas publikely married at <hi>Sterling</hi> by the Bishop of <hi>Orkney</hi> to the ſaid Earle <hi>Bothwell,</hi> notvvithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that he had then tvvo vviues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue,<note place="margin">Alſo the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction aforeſaid and the ſcotiſh monuments.</note> and vvas diuorſed from the third (called dame <hi>Iane Gorden</hi>) vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adulterie by himſelfe committed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Ione</hi> Queene of <hi>Naples</hi> had no long fruition of her inordinate luſt and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous marriage vvith the ſaide Duke of <hi>Tarent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Colin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tius lib. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>216.</hi> &amp; <hi>218</hi>
               </note> for he being therfore deteſted of all the countrey, pined avvay shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vvithimmoderate venery &amp; thought,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Marie</hi> queene of <hi>Scotland</hi> after that adulterous marriage had vvith <hi>Both<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Buconan fol. <hi>199.</hi> &amp; <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>95.</hi> lib. <hi>18.</hi> &amp; <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> did but a ſmall time enioy him, for the Nobilitie and the commons, riſing in armes againſt them, put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both to their ſeuerall shifts, firſt <hi>Both<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> to flee into <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and not long after that, the ſaide <hi>Marie</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> the vvhich <hi>Bothwell</hi> liuing or rather languishing in priſon and like a banished and conſumed man, had there nothing ſo comfortable to his guiltie conſcience, as preſent death, vvhich there alſo aftervvard enſued.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Ione</hi> Queene of <hi>Naples</hi> raiſed a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable ſciſme and diuiſion in <hi>Italie</hi> and <hi>Fraunce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Colinutius lib. <hi>5.</hi> Mexia in vita Vencelai. Platina in vitae Clementis v. &amp; vita vrbani. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> by reaſon of tvvo Popes at one time, <hi>Vrban</hi> pope at <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Clement</hi> pope at <hi>Auinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie</hi> the Scottish queene did ſovv the ſeede of ſciſme and ſedition,<note place="margin">B. roſe at his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminution <hi>26.</hi> octobris, <hi>1571.</hi>
               </note> both in the church of <hi>England</hi> and of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by the meanes of three Popes, <hi>Pius</hi> moſt impious to her Maieſtie,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:5"/>
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> the xiij. and <hi>Sextus</hi> the fift novve Pope,<note place="margin">His book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of the Scottiſhe Queenes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. fo 20. Her letters to the B. of <hi>Gloſco</hi> written in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher dated, 6. Nouember. 1577. Her letters to French &amp; Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours.</note> vvhich vvhat vvith the brutish bull, vvhat vvith ſundry thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts of excommunication pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by her meanes and her mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, vvhat vvith diſpenſations giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all thoſe that vvould in her fauour rebell againſt the Queene our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Ladie, haue not onely ſought to vvithdravve the hearts of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties euill diſpoſed ſubiectes from their naturall loue &amp; due obedience, but alſo haue bene the impulſiue and principall cauſe of all Sciſmes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnnaturall diſſenſions vvithin her Maieſties kingdoms and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ione</hi> Queene of <hi>Naples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Petrus Mexia, in vita Vencelai.</note> ſent to the Pope of <hi>Auinion</hi> called by many hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers <hi>Antipope Clement,</hi> a Pope of her ovvne facture &amp; fashion, to vphold and defend her quarrell againſt <hi>Charles</hi> forces, vvho by reaſon that he vvas Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phevve of <hi>Lewes</hi> king of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſonne (according to ſome vvriters) or (as
<pb facs="tcp:8764:5"/>ſome ſay) next of kinne to <hi>Andreas</hi> or <hi>Andraſius</hi> her firſt husband king of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> by her murdered, vvas Competitor vvith her in the ſaid kingdome,<note place="margin">Collinuti us lib. <hi>8.</hi> pag. <hi>215.</hi> &amp; <hi>224.</hi>
               </note> &amp; that by the title of <hi>Robert</hi> king of <hi>Naples</hi> her grandfathers teſtament, &amp; alſo by kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſent many times to the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> not ſo much for the defence of her ſelf and her ſonne in the kingdome of <hi>Scotlande,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lph</hi> an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t her meſſenger in this behalfe. B. <hi>Roſ</hi> &amp; his let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters confeſsion 26 Octob. 1571 Her letters to B. of <hi>Glaſco.</hi> Her letters to euerie of the Ambaſſadors French &amp; Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. Her letters to <hi>Morgan</hi> her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in <hi>France,</hi> and his letters to her. Her moſt ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful letter to the Engliſh and Scottiſh bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, <hi>If e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Prince. Iohn Hameltons</hi> letters to her 6. Iulij. 1571. &amp; the Duke of <hi>Aluas</hi> meſſage ſent by him. B. <hi>Roſe.</hi> letters emploiment by her in <hi>Germani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Father <hi>Henr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> meſſage from her to the princes combined, for the contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards the inuaſion of the Realme, and putting her in actuall poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame.</note> as (vvhich is far vvorſe) to the berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of her Maieſtie of her rightfull crovvne and dignitie royall, partlie in that vvith her priuitie tenne hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſande crovvnes vvere im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied by the Pope vppon any that vvould ſet vp in <hi>England</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholike religion, and aduance her to the Crovvne in poſſeſsion, partlie in that shee gaue maintenance to her Maieſties knovven Rebels both in <hi>Flaunders</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> partly in that shee practiſed inuaſion by forraine forces, and actuall Rebellion by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall Subiects in theſe her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb facs="tcp:8764:6"/>Realmes of <hi>Englande</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Ione</hi> Queene of <hi>Naples</hi> ſent alſo at that time,<note place="margin">Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rus exi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Collinutiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Blondi hiſtoria. Paulus Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</note> and to the ſame end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to <hi>Charles</hi> the french king, and to <hi>Lewes</hi> Duke of <hi>Aniew</hi> the ſaide frenche kings vncle: requeſting them to bring all the forces they poſſibly could to the ſubduing of <hi>Charles</hi> her competitor in the kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſent many times to king <hi>Phillip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At one of thoſe times <hi>Oſmond Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon</hi> the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, B. <hi>Roſe</hi> the procurer, the Spaniſhe Ambaſſad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur the performer of men &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. At one time thentrie was appointed at <hi>Harwich</hi> in <hi>Suffolk</hi> inuaſion confeſſed by <hi>Throgmorton.</hi> Her let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to <hi>Babington.</hi> Her letters to the Spaniſh Ambaſſador, &amp; the confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Babington</hi> and his confederates, and the confeſsion of her own Secretaries. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Henries</hi> meſſage betweene her and the Pope and the combined Princes.</note> and to her vncle the Duke of <hi>Cuiſe,</hi> and other princes combined to bring their forces, not to preſerue her in her poſſeſsion of the kingdome of <hi>Scotlande,</hi> but to the inuaſion of this Realme of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and ſubduing of her Maieſtie the moſte lavvefull and vndoubted Queene of the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Ione</hi> the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Queene in regard that the ſaide <hi>Lewes</hi> Duke of <hi>Aniow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collinutius.</note> vvould defend and protect her againſt the ſaid <hi>Charles,</hi> offered to make him her ſonne by adoption, and that he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie after her death should ſucceede her, both in the kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> &amp; alſo of <hi>Sicelie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie</hi> the Scottish Queen in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that king <hi>Phillip</hi> shoulde take her vvholy in his protection,<note place="margin">Proued by her letters to the ſaid Spaniſh Ambaſſadour <hi>Barnard de Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by her Secretaries, <hi>Naw and Curle.</hi>
               </note> &amp; likevviſe the ſtate and affaires of this Countrie, promiſed to giue &amp; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to him by her laſt vvill and teſtament the right (vvhich shee pretended to haue) both to the ſucceſsion of the crovvne of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ione</hi> Queene of <hi>Naples</hi> had great &amp; mightie Princes to take her part both out of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and from Prouince, but both shee and all that held on her ſide, had ſo ſtrange a fortune and deſaſter, as it is vvonderfull, for the Pope by her
<pb facs="tcp:8764:7"/>meanes exalted vvas depoſed, the ſaid Duke of <hi>Aniew</hi> Generall of the fielde that came into <hi>Ialie</hi> (as <hi>Pandulphus Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut us</hi> vvriteth) vvith fifty thouſand men and (as <hi>Peter Mexia</hi> affirmeth) thirtie thouſand of them horſ-men,<note place="margin">Collmitius lib. <hi>5. ſo. 228.</hi> Mexia in vita Ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elai.</note> died by the vvay, and xvi. Barons, and moſt of his gallant companie vvith him, and the re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that ſuruiued returned home vvith more shame than vvith pride they came foorth, begging all the vvay as they vvent by tvvo or three in a companie (as <hi>Platina</hi> vvitneſſeth) and the Queene her her ſelf vvas taken priſoner by him,<note place="margin">Platina in vita V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bani. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> shee firmelie hoped to haue conquered and ſlaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie</hi> the Scottiſh Queen vvhich had in <hi>Rome</hi> at ſeurall times three Popes, in <hi>Spaine</hi> king <hi>Phillip,</hi> in <hi>Fraunce</hi> the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotlande,</hi> Dukes, Earles, Lordes,<note place="margin">The proof of theſe is publik and moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious.</note> Gentlemen, and others too too manie bent to accompliſhe her vnquiet humor and ſeditious deſſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet neither had shee nor anie
<pb facs="tcp:8764:7"/>that tooke her part any proſperous ſucces, for 2 of her beſt friends of the three Popes died, king <hi>Phillip</hi> hath neuer been vvithout ciuill vvarres and his handes full of vprores &amp; dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tumults, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſo megre and ſo croſſed in all his deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeinements, that he could not at any time helpe her, nor vvell releeue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the Dukes, Earles, and Lords, for the moſt part that tooke her part either haue loſte their goods, liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodes, lands, liberties, and countries, or haue been ſlaine of others, or haue ſlaine themſelues, many Gentlemen hanged for her ſake to the perpetuall infamie of them &amp; their race, &amp; vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vndoing of all their poſteritie, &amp; as touching her ſelf neither her ovvn land could abide her, nor the Ocean Sea (to vvhoſe mercie in extreame refuge she committed herſelf) could brooke her, nor the land of <hi>England</hi> (vvhere shee hath remained aboue xvi. yeeres in our Soueraigne Ladie Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> protection) could
<pb facs="tcp:8764:8"/>for the more part from her firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming like her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parrie</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of her truſtie man <hi>Morgans</hi> dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with him for murdering of the Quene. The conſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Naw, Curle,</hi> and all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators.</note> or be liked of her, and she became all that vvhile priſoner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, vvhoſe Royall perſon she con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie hoped and often practized to haue murdered.</p>
            <p>Laſt of al,<note place="margin">Leonardus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retinus in hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Florentina, Collinutiut. Mexia. Paulus Aemili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> 
               <hi>Jone</hi> Queen of <hi>Naples</hi> being taken by <hi>Charles</hi> nephevv to <hi>Lewes</hi> king of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and the firſt King of <hi>Naples</hi> of that name, vvas by the ſaide <hi>Charles</hi> vppon the aduiſe taken and had of the ſaid King <hi>Lewes,</hi> ſtrangled in priſon and ſo (by Gods prouidence) paid the death (as the hiſtory vvitneſſeth) that she gaue to her firſt huſband <hi>An reas</hi> King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mexia in vita Vencelai.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marie</hi> Queen of <hi>Scotland</hi> although by fleeing out of her ovvn Realme of <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>Englande,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide Buconaenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fol. <hi>199.</hi> &amp; <hi>200.</hi>
               </note> and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnder the Queene of <hi>Englands</hi> protection, shee eſcaped hitherto the due reuengement of her ſaid husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds death,<note place="margin">This appeareth by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the duke of Norfolke &amp; others, which met the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Lordes at <hi>yorke</hi> that came thither, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring iuſtice in that behalf.</note> vvhen and vvhere the chiefeſt of the Nobilitie of <hi>Scotland</hi> purſued
<pb facs="tcp:8764:8"/>her by iuſtice: yet becauſe she hath ſundrie times ſince that time conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to deſtroy the ſacred perſon of her Maieſty, and being once or tvviſe pardoned, hath falne into a relapſe or recination, there hath been vppon due hearing and examination of the vvhol matter, together vvith her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall anſvveares taken by the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Lordes of the Realme,<note place="margin">The Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t 27. <hi>regni Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethae.</hi>
               </note> aſsiſted vvith the principall Iudges of the ſame, ſentence pronounced by them againſt her <hi>According to the Statute of aſſociation by Herſelfe ſubſigned and allowed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her owne let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And thus shee to the ioy of all good Chriſtians and vvell affected English, hath had Gods iudgement in her acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished and performed, that did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie kill her firſt husband, King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but compaſſed alſo ſundrie times the death of her Maieſtie Queene of <hi>England,</hi> and conſequentlie vvas like to bring the vvhole Realme in danger of a generall maſſacre and preſent deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:9"/>had not the eternall and Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lorde of his vnſpeakable and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed goodneſſe by a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous diſcouerie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:9"/>
            <head>The ſecond Chapter containing <hi>a ſecond Analogie or Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance</hi> betvveene the Emperor Licinius <hi>and the ſaid</hi> Marie <hi>Queene of</hi> Scotland.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>A ſecond preſident much reſembling the caſe</hi> in queſtion, is offered vnto vs from our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieman and moſt Chriſtian Emperor <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the Great, who commaunded the death of <hi>Licinius</hi> the Emperor, and yet this act was neuer controlled by any writer.</p>
            </argument>
            <div type="history">
               <head>The Hiſtorie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in open hoſtilitie, <hi>Licinius</hi> conſort with him in the Empire,<note place="margin">Euſebius. Socrates. Sozomenus. Sigonius de im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio occidentali. Mexia in vitis Conſtantini, Marentii, &amp; Licinii.</note> who fauoured the Heathen, perſecuted the Chriſtians, and came in armes to violate his perſon, yet at the requeſt of <hi>Conſtantia</hi> his ſiſter, wife to the ſaid <hi>Licinius,</hi> he ſpared his life, &amp; bound him to remaine at <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media,</hi> in the Prouince of <hi>Bithinia.</hi> But when afterwards <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:8764:10"/>that the ſaide <hi>Licinius</hi> attempted a new inſurrection and was to that purpoſe confedered with other Princes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor put to death his Colledge Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Licinius</hi> and neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> and ſought to flee away from the place appointed, than did he foorthwith commaund the ſaid <hi>Lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> to be put to death in the xv: yeere of the ſaid <hi>Conſtantines</hi> raigne when hee was lx. yeeres of age, and in the yeere of our Lord God <hi>377.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="comparison">
               <head>
                  <hi>The compariſon and</hi> reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance betweene theſe two caſes, is verie like.</head>
               <p>Firſt <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Licinius</hi> vvere both choſen Lordes and Princes of the Empire.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queene of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> Queene of <hi>Scotland</hi> vvere both called to the ſtate of kinges in the yle of <hi>Britanie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Empire of <hi>Britanie</hi> diuided into two king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, as the Empire in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> time was into two Empires.</note> although in diuers diſtinct kingdomes: and therfore the doinges of <hi>Licinius</hi> mought ſeeme to haue more colour of right to the Empire, than <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titule
<pb facs="tcp:8764:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>herſelfe in this Realme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marie</hi> queene of Scotland but a titularie queene. Kings of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land haue been feudaturies, &amp; done homage to the kings of England.</note> beeing alſo but a titularie Queen in her ovvn land: &amp; as it appeareth by the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles and by auncient recordes, her Progenitors haue done homage for their kingdomes to the crovvne of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> notvvithſtanding manie princelie benefites receiued at the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Conſtantins</hi> hands,<note place="margin">Euſebius.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Socrates.</note> inſomuch that he vvas aduaunced by him to the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of his ovvne ſiſter <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> vvhich deſcended from a princelie progenie of kings: yet, contrarie to his oath and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe like an vngratefull man he became a profeſſed enemie to <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> albeit shee receaued manie great fauours at the hands of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in ſauing both her honour and life,<note place="margin">Scotland in an. <hi>1568.</hi> England. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> reg. Eliz.</note> vvhen she vvas ſo earneſtlie purſued by the Lordes and the commons both of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> yet like an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull perſon shee did shevve her
<pb facs="tcp:8764:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelfe contrarie to her vovved promiſe an apparant enemie to the Queene of <hi>England.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Her letters to the B. of <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> &amp; to <hi>B. Roſe Morgan,</hi> and <hi>Mendoza.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> vvould alone haue bin Lord and prince of the Empire by the remoue of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Marie</hi> vvoulde bee the onelie Queene of <hi>Britanie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diuers books and pedegrees publiſhed by her agents and fauorites to that effect. <hi>Reſignatio facta</hi> 1567. <hi>Vide Buconanum fol.</hi> 196. And Holing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheds Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, fol. 388.</note> and not onlie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon her ovvne ſonne from the kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> (after that she had reſigned the ſame vnto him) but alſo expell her Maieſtie Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> from her proper &amp; vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted kingdome of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> vſurped an vniuſt title, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe the vniuerſall Emperor.</p>
               <p>So did <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotlande</hi> giue long ſince,<note place="margin">In the booke called <hi>Expoſitio canſarum.</hi> And ſhe did it at her entrie into <hi>Poitiers</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and would not be reduced from the allowing of the ſame in all her proceedings ouer ſince.</note> both the title and armes of <hi>England,</hi> vſurping therein the roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtate of her Maieſtie and crovvne of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> came not vvillinglie vnto <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> but by force of armes vvas taken at <hi>Chryſopolis</hi> a Citie vvithin the prouince of <hi>Bithinia,</hi> and brought to <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> came not vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie into the lande and dominion of our Soueraigne Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hollingſheds Chronicle. fol. 392.</note> but being encountred vvith her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, &amp; enforced to leaue the field, came by boate into <hi>Werkington</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the vveſt marches of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> had his life once pardoned for open hoſtilitie againſt the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mexia in vita Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantini. ca. <hi>1.</hi> Euſebius, Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Sozomenus.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotlande</hi> hath had her life ſpared for murdring her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; alſo for hoſtilitie and treaſon pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed againſt <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queene of <hi>England.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">13. <hi>regni Reginae Elizabethae</hi> publiſhed in Parliament.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> although pardoned,<note place="margin">Mexia. cap. <hi>10.</hi> Socrates lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> Sozomenus lib. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> yet vvas not too far truſted by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> but firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fined to <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> &amp; aftervvards to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and there had a noble gard about his palace and perſon.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Marie</hi> of Scotland,<note place="margin">Iuſtlie miſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted for giuing the armes and title of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ratifie the treatie of <hi>Edingburg</hi> and afterward for procuring the rebellion in the North, and manie other treaſons ſince ſhe had for her abode Carlile caſtle, Bolton Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Sheffeld caſtle, all at the Queene of Englands great charges and expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> and great fauours, vvas vpon moſt iuſt cauſe miſtruſted, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to certaine ſtatelie houſes in <hi>England,</hi> &amp; there had princely main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and an honourable gard at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending her perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> did ſeeke to flee avvay from the place vvhereunto he vvas enioyned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotlande</hi> did manie times practiſe the like in <hi>England.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Confeſſed by her before the Lords at <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dringa</hi> caſtle.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> did treat vvith diuers princes and captaines to make nevv vvarres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> did not onlie practiſe vvith diuers princes,<note place="margin">The practiſe of bringing in of forces co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed by her before the Lords.</note> Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and others, to bring in forreine forces into the Realme of <hi>Englande,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bington, Ballard</hi> and other of that conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and moſt horrible trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> but alſo did conſpire and contriue vvith euil diſpoſed ſubiectes to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8764:12"/>the chaunge of the ſtate, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrovve of religion, the death of her Maieſties ſacred perſon, the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre of the nobilitie, and an vniuerſal deſolation of the vvhole Realme.</p>
               <p>To conclude,<note place="margin">Mexia in vita Conſtantini. ca. <hi>1</hi> Socrates &amp; So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomenus <hi>in the foreſaid places.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Licinius</hi> for endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againe <hi>Conſtantines</hi> perſon and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by nevv troubles to aſpire to the Empire like as <hi>Maximinianus</hi> before had done, vvas by the appointment of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> adiudged to die,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath giuen far greater cauſe to our <hi>Conſtantine Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> Queen of <hi>England</hi> to fear nevv conſpiracies both againſt her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie &amp; the ſtate of the vvhole realme, like as the ſaid <hi>Marie</hi> and other her confederates haue manie times done before,<note place="margin">In the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden 13. Elizabeth.</note> and therefore ſhe had been in the high court of Parliament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to die manie yeeres paſt, but that her Maieſtie of her ſingular and great clemencie ſpared to giue her aſſent thereunto, and of late againe
<pb facs="tcp:8764:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>vpon an other horrible conſpiracie there is by the chiefeſt Lordes and Iudges of this Realme ſentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt her, Proclamation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon and due execution reſpectiuely made according to an act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the xxvii. yeere of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties raigne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The thirde Chapter conteining <hi>certaine preſidentes of ſundrie</hi> Emperours and Kinges vvhich <hi>haue put other Princes vnto</hi> death.</head>
            <p>HOwbeit wee neede not farder by enſample to ſhewe that one Prince hath put another vnto death, yet for the farther warrant, and quiet of princes mindes, and to ſtoppe the euill ſpeeches of ſuch, whoſe heades are wholy buſied in Princes matters: it is not amiſſe vnto the former exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to adde, firſt certaine preſidentes of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, then of Kinges, and laſtly for thoſe euill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected ſort (vnto whome the actions of the Pope are their beſt inſtructions) the doings and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſundry Popes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſtantin</hi> ſo much renovvmed in the church of God, and that amongeſt other his princelie vertues, for his ſingular clemencie, and care in religion, did cauſe to bee put to death, not onely the Emperour <hi>Licinius</hi> as before, but alſo <hi>Maximinianus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The loue of the countrey knoweth no kinted.</note> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Emperour beeing detected by his daughter, vvife of the ſaide <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> for an horrible conſpiracie againſt her
<pb facs="tcp:8764:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>husbande, and yet conſider, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> shevved vnto him all duties of humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and courteſie, in ſo much that hee married his daughter, &amp; receiued him vnder his protection giuing vnto him all princely entertainement, at vvhat time hee vvas purſued by his vvicked ſonne <hi>Maxentius</hi> to death. yet conſider, vvhen ſo many benefites of this Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour could not ſtay him,<note place="margin">Ambition no leſſe vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full than blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</note> but in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a kingdome, hee thought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue his protector of life, then <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> loath to nourish in his boſome anie ſuch ſerpent, commaunded his death, and ſaued himſelfe.</p>
            <p>An other like example is that of <hi>Rheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuporis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A ſecond preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of an Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour.</note> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> calleth him, or as <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> &amp; <hi>Liuie, Thraſipolis,</hi> king of <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> vvho by <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour vvas put to death.<note place="margin">Cornelius Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus lib. <hi>2.</hi> anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium.</note> For vvhe ras the ſaid <hi>Rheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuporis</hi> had compaſſed the death of king <hi>Cotys,</hi> for that hee coulde not abide to haue him confort vvith him in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Thraſia,</hi> vvhich in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> daies vvas deuided betvveene them, the
<pb facs="tcp:8764:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſayd <hi>Rheſcuporis</hi> vvas accuſed by queene <hi>Cotys</hi> to the Emperour and Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> for this his villanous fact in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying her husbande, vvhere he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued iudgement both of depriuation of his kingdome, and alſo of banishment: but aſſoone as he vvent about to flee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Alexandria</hi> (vvhere he vvas confined &amp; vvith a ſtrong garde honored againſt his vvill) the Emperour <hi>Tiberius</hi> preſentlie gaue in commandement to behead him:<note place="margin">Bloud thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth after bloud.</note> and yet the ſaid king, did neuer practiſe the death of the Emperour, as <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath practiſed the death of the Queene of <hi>Englande,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Holling ſheds chronicle.</note> and that ſince the ſaid <hi>Marie</hi> came to be a titulary Queene and had giuen ouer to her ſonne Kinge <hi>Iemie</hi> to be the onely and abſolute king of <hi>Scotlande.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An other preſident I find in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth of that name,<note place="margin">The third pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of an Emperour.</note> vvho conuincing <hi>Robert</hi> king of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Prouince</hi> of open rebellion &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie vvith his ſubiectes againſt his perſon and Empire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter Mexia</hi> in the life of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</note> ſummoned him to
<pb facs="tcp:8764:15"/>appeare, and finally by proceſſe of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice gaue ſentence of death againſt him depriuing him of his kingdome of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A king for trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon depoſed &amp; ſentenced to death.</note> and diſcharging all his vaſſals of their homage and fidelitie that they ovved him, and farther gaue licence to <hi>Fredericke</hi> king of <hi>Sicelie,</hi> the ſaid king <hi>Roberts</hi> enimie, to make a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt of the ſaid kingdom in the behalf of his ſonne.</p>
            <p>Thus farre goeth the Hiſtorie,<note place="margin">Clementin de re iudicata. c. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoralis.</note> hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeuenth in his <hi>Clementine</hi> calleth the ſaide <hi>Robert</hi> king of <hi>Sicely</hi> according to the old error of Popes,<note place="margin">Fazellus de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Siculis.</note> and not of <hi>Naples,</hi> according to all old vvriters, and found fault in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſentence about the manner of proceeding and not the matter in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, for he doth not call in queſtion the ſaid iudgement as though it had bin vnlavvefull for him to haue put the ſaid king to death for treaſon, if he had bin founde vvithin anye of his dominions, vvhere he had committed anie ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible crime againſt him, but in that hee did cite him out of that diſtrict and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites
<pb facs="tcp:8764:15"/>of the Empire, to vvit out of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> (vvhich the Pope calleth <hi>Sicely,</hi> vvhere had beene euer his continuall and notorious reſidence) to the citie of <hi>Piſa,</hi> a place iuſtly feared moſt daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to his perſon: but if the ſaide king <hi>Robert</hi> had contriued the death of the Emperour vvithin the iuriſdiction of the Empire, and there had beene founde or (as it is vvoont to bee vſed in criminall cauſes) had beene ſent thither to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere the contempt doone againſt his Maieſtie, then &amp; in that caſe, Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> did agnize and inſert in expreſſe vvoordes in his <hi>Clementine</hi> published in the Councell of <hi>Vienna,</hi> that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour mought haue ſentenced the ſayde king lavvfullie to death,<note place="margin">Popes cenſure in what caſe a Prince may lentence an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawfullie to death.</note> his vvordes are theſe: <hi>Quòd ſi punitio criminis intra di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictum imperialem commiſſi ad imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem forſan pertinuiſſe aſſeratur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>d c</hi> paſteralis.</note> 
               <hi>verum eſt quidem, ſi ineodem diſtrictu fuiſſet inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus delinquens, vel ad illum de more remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> Wherein hee doth agree very vvell vvith the ciuill lavv, vvhich is that, <hi>ſortitur quis forum, tàm ratione delicti, quàm rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one
<pb facs="tcp:8764:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>domicilij,</hi> that is, a man may be vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of an other Princes iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction and prerogatiue, aſvvell in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of his offence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, as of his place of dvvelling: the diſcourſe vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, more at large hereafter.</p>
            <p>In like maner <hi>Barnard</hi> king of <hi>Italie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Barnard</hi> king of <hi>Italie</hi> put to death, by <hi>Lewes</hi> the French king.</note> being perſvvaded by the Clergie of his right and title that he had to the crovvn of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> leuied an armie intending to recouer his right, and to deſtroie them that than poſſeſſed in the kingdome: but in the firſt encounter he vvas taken,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Belleforeſt</hi> in his French hiſtory</note> had his eies put out, a vvhile vvas kept in priſon, and after by <hi>Lewes Debonaire</hi> king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and Emperour for the better aſſurance of his ſtate commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be put to death.</p>
            <p>So likevviſe <hi>Conradine</hi> king of <hi>Sicelie</hi> vvas by <hi>Manfredus</hi> priſoned:<note place="margin">Collmitius lib. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> he bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed his kingdome to <hi>Conradine</hi> his ſonne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conradine</hi> put to death by king <hi>Charles.</hi>
               </note> the vvhich being yong and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make reſiſtaunce left his countrie vnto <hi>Manfrede,</hi> the vvhich <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of <hi>Aniew</hi> &amp; <hi>Prouence,</hi> the French kings
<pb facs="tcp:8764:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>brother at the requeſt of the Cleargie of <hi>Italie</hi> manie yeres after, ſubdued &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and there beeing choſen and crovvned king of <hi>Naples</hi> in his daies, <hi>Conradine</hi> being grovven to yeres, and deſirous of his fathers kingdome by his father giuen him, much holpen and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the perſonall preſence of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie great princes, hee entred the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in vvarlike maner: vvhere he vvas ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoner, and after tvvelue moneths impriſonment, by the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the beſt learned in the lavve, in open iudgement hee vvas condemned, and publikelie vvith manie his confederates hee vvas commaunded by the ſame <hi>Charles</hi> to be executed. So vvhen <hi>Lewes</hi> king of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie</hi> vvas conſulted by his nephevve <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collinutius li. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> vvhat hee vvere beſt to doe vvith <hi>Ione Neapolitan</hi> Queene, than his priſoner,<note place="margin">An aduiſe of a king for a queene to be put to death.</note> hee ſent tvvo noble men vnto the ſaid <hi>Charles</hi> vvith this determinate anſvvere &amp; aduiſe that ſhe ſhould be brought to the ſame place vvher ſhe ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled her husband, &amp; there to be ſtrangled in like maner her ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>The iiij. Chapter conteining</hi> the Actes and iudgements of ſundrie Popes, which haue approued the <hi>death of ſome princes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT to leaue the examples of kings, and to come to Popes, vvhoſe acts vvill better ſerue to ſatisfie ſome mens humors, than all the Preſidentes of Kinges and Emperours, be they neuer ſo godlie:<note place="margin">The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſay a Pope may erre in maners but not in iudgement.</note> if Popes cannot erre (as Popes doe affirme) than Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth his example vvere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perſvvade in this caſe euen Pope <hi>Sextus Quintus</hi> himſelfe, novv Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> although he be one of the chiefe pillers and patrones of the Scottishe Queene,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A iudgement of</hi> Clement <hi>of putting a king to death</hi> Colimutius in hiſtoria Neapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litana. lib. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>186.</hi> Henricus Gildi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingenſit in hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Auſtriaca.</note> for that the ſaid <hi>Clement</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered for lavv in <hi>Conradine</hi> the king of <hi>Sicelie</hi> his caſe, that becauſe he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed to take avvay the life of <hi>Charles</hi> the king of <hi>Naples,</hi> it vvas both lavvfull and expedient for the ſaide <hi>Charles</hi> to put him to death.<note place="margin">An other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a Pope.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And taking vvith vs the ſaid Popes
<pb facs="tcp:8764:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ground and <hi>maxime,</hi> that Popes cannot erre: a ſecond example vvill ſerue of an other Pope called <hi>Boniface,</hi> vvho put to death the Pope <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> vvhom hee had in priſon for a leſſer cauſe a great deale then that of <hi>Conradine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collinutius li. <hi>5.</hi> Vide Cornelium Agrippa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate ſcientiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> c. de eccleſ. magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratibus; de tribus mirabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Bonifacii.</note> 
               <hi>Metuens</hi> (as the hiſtory ſetteth dovvn in expreſſe termes) <hi>ne ob ſingularem pietatem ad pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denuo reuocaretur:</hi> that is, becauſe hee feared that <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the olde Pope vvould for his ſingular vertue bee called to his Popedome againe: thus did <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> not for anie treaſon practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, but for feare of looſing his liuing put <hi>Celeſtine</hi> a good Pope to death.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Pope in creating of Cardinals,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cardinals in their creation Popes felowes.</hi> Gigas de crimine laeſae maieſtatis. Iulius clarus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptarum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiarum. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> calleth them the Princes of this vvorlde, and his brethren part of his body, making therfore the crime of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, called <hi>crimen laeſae maieſtatis</hi> to lie in offence done to their perſons aſvvell as to himſelf, as is by <hi>Gigas</hi> and <hi>Iulius Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> affirmed: I thinke the iudgement of Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſixt, may be conioyned
<pb facs="tcp:8764:18"/>vvith that former preſident of <hi>Boniface</hi> the viii. vvho, hauing gotten viii. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals in priſon, did for the preſeruation of his ovvne perſon (as hee did pretend) cauſe fiue of them to bee put in ſacks and being therein faſt bound to be caſt into the ſea:<note place="margin">Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> put to death 8. Cardinals for preſeruation of his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Collinutius li.</hi> 5.</note> the other iii. being conuic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Genua</hi> in open iudgement he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be beheaded, and their bodies to be dried in an ouen, and to bee carried vvith their three purple Hats borne vp before him,<note place="margin">A ſtrange cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of a pope vpon dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of his owne felowes.</note> vvhen hee vvent any vvaies foorth, to the intent that this mought bee a terror vnto all other that shoulde contriue anie thing againſt his holines.</p>
            <p>And leaſt anie Romane Catholike shoulde thinke that it is an vnchriſtian part to put a chriſtian Queen to death, I giue him the ſame Pope <hi>Vrbans</hi> action for his inſtruction, vvho vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſvvord vvas brought al blooddy vnto him,<note place="margin">Collinutius. li. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> vvith the vvhich <hi>Charles</hi> king of <hi>Naples</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phevve to <hi>Lewes</hi> king of <hi>Hungary</hi> vvas by treacherie murdered at <hi>Buda</hi> in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garte</hi> (not vvithout the due punishment
<pb facs="tcp:8764:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God inflicted vppon the murderers and their abbettors for the ſame) hee allovving the facte,<note place="margin">A Popes allow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aunce of the treacherous murdering of a king.</note> handled the ſaide ſvvorde ſo embrued vvith bloud in his hande, and tooke great pleaſure in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If a Pope made allowance of ſo treacherous a murder of a good king, what diſalowance is there to bee made of a iust and honorable ſentence giuen of a tumultuous Queene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this is that Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Platina</hi> in the life of <hi>Vrban</hi> the vi. <hi>Collinutius li.</hi> 5. <hi>Mexia</hi> in the life of <hi>Vence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus.</hi>
               </note> (as <hi>Platina</hi> ſaith) vvhich not long before did aduaunce the ſayde <hi>Charles,</hi> vvith all the bleſsinges and aide that he could in his title &amp; claim againſt the ſaid <hi>Ione</hi> to the kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> pronouncing his curſe againſt her, as a ſciſmatike and rebell, and that notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, he aftervvards fell as faſt to the curſing of the ſaide <hi>Charles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collinutius. li. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> becauſe he vvould not create one <hi>Bitillus</hi> a bitelhed and verie levvde perſon, the ſaide Popes nephevv to be Prince of <hi>Capua,</hi> &amp; Lord of <hi>Dirachium</hi> in <hi>Dalmatia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe fevve examples vvhere kinges,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Emperours and Popes, haue put other princes of like condition to death, may ſerue in caſe of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Queene to perſvvade any man, that is not too too farre diſtempered in his iudgement, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciallye ſeeing the practiſes of theſe, vvhich for their treaſonable demerites, vvere put to death, are far inferior to this her moſt horrible and treacherous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, and that there can neuer be one hiſtorie, or example ſhovven in ſuch vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to this, vvhere a Queen hath had ſo many times her honor, and life preſerued, vvhen her ovvne ſubiects vvere in armes againſt her in <hi>Scotlande,</hi> vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her Nobilitie for the murdering of the king her husbande, craued her death by Iuſtice in <hi>England,</hi> &amp; vvhen the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and commons of <hi>England</hi> for nevv and freſh conſpiracies, and by her often reiterated againſt the Queenes Maieſtie and the good eſtate of the land, haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and againe, earneſtly requeſted both in open Parliaments, and els vvhere due execution of iuſtice againſt her.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A confirmation by manie <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons gathered out of the Ciuill and</hi> Canon lavve, of the honorable ſentence and execution paſt againſt <hi>the Scottiſh Queene.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I proceede to the inſtifying of the ſayde ſentence and execution, I thinke it not amiſſe, here to ſet downe what the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> haue beene in theſe Capitall offences, not only from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors time, but from the beginning of any Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire or principallity within this Realme: &amp; ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what hath beene written herein, I finde, that the very imagination and intent of treaſon, being in the higheſt degree without ouert facte, hath in the times of all Kinges, and in all perſons, beene loſſe of life and member, loſſe of goods and lands, and perpetuall corruption of bloud: which Lawe agreeth verie well &amp; ſeemeth to haue commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and beginning from a Ciuill conſtitution, made by the famous Emperors <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi> in the yeare of our Lorde God. 3 8 9. The effect of which Lawe, for the matter in queſtion fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:<note place="margin">L. quiſquis C. ad L Iulian ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatis.</note> 
               <hi>Quiſquis de nece principis eorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> qui conſilijs principis interſunt &amp;c. cogitauerit (eadem enim ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate voluntatem ſceleris, qua effectum puniri iura volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt) ipſe quidem, vt maieſtatis reus, gladio feriatur, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis eius omnibus fiſco noſtro addictis.</hi> Whoſoeuer ſhall imagine or intend the death of the king or any of his counſell (for the Lawes would with the ſame ſeueritie haue a man puniſhed, aſwel for his wil in
<pb facs="tcp:8764:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>intending as for his fact in committing treaſon) hee ſhalbe beheaded, as guiltie of high treaſon, and his goods forfaited to our Exchequer.</p>
            <p>Note here, that the ſaide wordes bee generall and ſuffer no exception,<note place="margin">L. <hi>4. C.</hi> ad L. Iulian maiesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> which alſo is in the verie next Conſtitution precedent by three other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, <hi>Valentinian, Valens</hi> and <hi>Gratian</hi> confirmed, where they vſe theſe wordes, <hi>In ſola cauſa laeſae maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis omnibus aequa conditio eſt, nulla habita, militie ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris vel dignitatis defenſione:</hi> In the onelie cauſe of treaſon all perſons are of egal condition, debarred from all defence and priuiledge of militarie ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, birth, or dignitie. And as the wordes of the law are generall including all perſons whoſoeuer, ſo is the ſelfeſame law generall, becauſe it recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth allowance in all countries, and in <hi>Scotland</hi> it ſelfe, where the ciuill lawe is exerciſed, and in that regard may be called <hi>Ius Gentium,</hi> the law of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>Quia eo iure omnes gentes vtuntur</hi> becauſe in all Nations the ſame law and penaltie for treaſon is vſed: wherein the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Queene coulde not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ignorance, ſeeing it is the lawe of her owne countrie, and the law of all the worlde, and ſeeing ſhe confeſſed her preſciencie &amp; knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as alſo of the ſtatute made in the ſame effect, the ſeuen and twentieth yeere of her Maieſties raigne, diſcouering in her letters to <hi>Babington,</hi> that if her conſpiracies were knowne to her Maieſtie, it were ſufficient for that Queene to incloſe her in ſome hole, foorth of which ſhe ſhould not eſcape, if ſo bee ſhee did not vſe her worſe: as though ſhee had ſaid the hainouſneſſe of her deſert and penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the lawe did inflict a greater puniſhment on
<pb facs="tcp:8764:20"/>her, than being kept cloſe priſoner, which ſhee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confeſſeth in plain words in her letter to <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza</hi> the Spaniſh Ambaſſador: <hi>Let this be kept ſecret, foraſmuch as if it come to bee reuealed, it ſhoulde bee in France the loſſe of my Dower, in Scotland a cleare breach with my ſome, and in this countrie, my totall ruine and deſtruction.</hi> And the ſaid ſtatute of the ſaide xxvij. yeere of her Maieſties raigne doth not alter the ſubſtance of the offence in treaſon, or make it more greeuous or preiudiciall than it was before: but for as much as her Maieſties life (whome Almightie God preſerue to the end of all time) was ſought by many wicked complots of deſperate miſcreants to bee taken away, and the publike peace diſturbed: the bodie of the whole Realme (to preuent that miſchiefe, &amp; that this might ſerue as an other war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſtay their furie) enacted and ſet downe a more honourable proceeding againſt all ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Competitors of the kingdome, than there was before therin, adding rather forme than ſubſtance, that if anie ſuch villanies were attempted, it might both in the matter and maner haue the more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable proceeding.</p>
            <p>Seeing than the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Queene is both by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall wordes and alſo by eſpeciall demonſtration within the compaſſe of the lawe, it remayneth to ſee what can be ſayde for her exemption from the ſayde lawe. I heare that principally alleaged for an excuſe, that ſhe was an abſolute Queene, and therefore in her perſon not to be impeached, as though it were to bee iuſtified by any lawe in the worlde, for a Queene to contriue the death of an other Queene, and that (which is moſt treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous)
<pb facs="tcp:8764:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>in her owne kingdome. Or that a King or Queene comming foorth of her owne Realme, to the kingdome and dominion of an other King or Queene, may there doe what they liſt without controlement, vnder colour of their kingly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue. And although I ſhould graunt that ſhe was an abſolute Queene, and in reſpect thereof, had diuers priuiledges incident vnto her perſon: yet in this caſe all priuiledges that goe to, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the perſon,<note place="margin">In caſe of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon no priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge will ſerue.</note> are excluded: <hi>Quia in cauſa laeſae maieſtatis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Baldus</hi>) <hi>priuilegiatus non poteſt alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare priuilegium.</hi> A man priuiledged in his perſon, in caſe of treaſon, cannot alledge his priuiledge.</p>
            <p>And this is a moſt general lawe and all perſons whoſoeuer are ſubiect to the ſame,<note place="margin">L. Q. in Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia vbi de cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine agi opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet.</note> that in what place they haue committed any crime, ther accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law of the place (without regard of any priuiledge) they ought to bee adiudged, <hi>Et hoc ius perpetuum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. edita de eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do <hi>C. 1.</hi> Inſt. de ſatiſdat. tutor. Parag. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſaith the Text: that is, this law is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, for ſo this word <hi>perpetuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> is in the ciuill law in ſundrie places vſed, and in this verie place it it is ſo by the learned expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. Neither can a king in in another kingdome challenge any ſuch preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto him, that for an offence giuen in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree he may not ther be puniſhed. For euerie king out of his own kingdome is to be accounted of,<note place="margin">Lapus de caſtillo allegat. <hi>92.</hi>
               </note> but as a priuate perſon, for that he hath no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>merum imperium,</hi> that is ſupreame and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute gouernment, but doth only reteine, <hi>honoris titulos &amp; dignitatis,</hi> the title of honor and dignitie within the territorie of an other king. So that ther where he hath offended <hi>per omnia diſtringitur etiam quoad perſonam,</hi> he may bee puniſhed in all that he
<pb facs="tcp:8764:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath &amp; that in his perſon,<note place="margin">zabarella. e pastoral. de re iudicata. D. D. c fi. de ſore competent.</note> for <hi>ratione delicti-ſortitur forum,</hi> by reaſon of his offence, hee is now become of another princes iuriſdiction and prerogatiue where he hath offended.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch that neither our friendes which are confedered with vs, nor Ambaſſadors which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from great &amp; mightie Princes are reſiant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, nor the kings and princes themſelues that carrie ſo great a maieſtie in their perſons can challenge any immunitie or priuiledge by reaſon of their confederacie, honor, or dignitie: but where they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract, &amp; where they offend, there muſt they abide the order of lawe &amp; condigne puniſhment. For of our friends that are in league &amp; amity with vs, heare what the law ſaith: <hi>Si ſint apud nos rei ex ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatibus confederatis in eos damnatos animaduertimus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">L non dubito ff. de captiuis de poſtlimiuio re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſis.</note> if anie perſon of the confedered Cities bee found guiltie amongeſt vs they are iuſticiable heere, and after their condemnation ſhall receiue execution accordingly.</p>
            <p>And of the Ambaſſadors, <hi>Iulius Paulus,</hi> who for his excellent skill in the law, came to be both <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſul</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> writeth in this maner:<note place="margin">L non aliàs pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag. legati ff. &amp; iudiciis.</note> 
               <hi>Legati ex delictis in legatione co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsis cogu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur iudicium Romae pati, ſiue ipſi admiſerint ſiue ſerui eorum.</hi> Ambaſſadors that are come to <hi>Rome</hi> out of far countries, are ther to anſwer for their offence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted there in time of the Embaſsie, whether it bee done by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues or any of their retinue.<note place="margin">L ſi legationis ff codem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tulo.</note> Likewiſe <hi>Saluius Iulianus</hi> the chiefe counſailer to <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor writeth thus: <hi>Si legationis tempore quis ſeruum vel aliam rem emerit, aut ex alia cauſa poſsidere cepit; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniquè cogetur e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accipere: aliter enim poteſtas daretur legatis ſub hac ſpecie res alienas domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auferendi:</hi> That is,<note place="margin">Note the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the law.</note> if any during his Embaſsie ſhall buy a bond-man or any
<pb facs="tcp:8764:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>thing els, or ſhall come to the poſſeſsion of any thing by any other title or meanes, he ſhalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to anſwere to the law in that behalfe, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe Ambaſſadors ſhould haue libertie vnder this colour to carry into their country other mens goods: but that ought not to bee graunted them, ſay the interpreters vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that law, <hi>Ne occaſio daretur delinquendi:</hi> leaſt an occaſion thereby ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them to deale lewdly.</p>
            <p>Then if a law will haue an Ambaſſadour as well as the ſubiect, to aunſwere vppon any contract or wrong done to the ſubiect, woulde the ſame lawe (trow you) allowe the practiſes of high treaſon in an Ambaſſador againſt the common peace vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed? And although ſome haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors haue had their liues ſpared them in caſes of high treaſon: yet that proueth not that for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they might not by law haue bin executed. For as <hi>Theodatus</hi> ſaid to the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Bizance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Procopius lib. <hi>1.</hi> de bello Gothoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> if an Ambaſſador ſhould in his Embaſsie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterie, or els vſe any villanie towards the Prince, <hi>Tunc quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Iuſtinum. lib.</hi> 7. in the caſe of adulterie.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; iure, legatum occidere pro humanis legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus licet:</hi> than were it lawfull by the law of the lande to put ſuch an Ambaſſadour to death. Wherfore <hi>Conradus Brunus</hi> writing both grauely &amp; learnedly of the dignitie &amp; immunitie of Ambaſſadors doth after a great diſcourſe, conclude with theſe words. <hi>Ius violandorum legatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ijs tantum ſeruandum eſſe, qui honeſte in legatione verſantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide L. per id te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus de curioſis. lib. <hi>12.</hi> &amp; L quoties &amp; L iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices de dignitat lib. <hi>12. C</hi> &amp;c iuarum nos pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag. verum. Ext. de priuilegiis.</note> the law that willeth no hands to be laid vpon an Ambaſſador, is to be kept with them only that doe in their Embaſsie behaue themſelues honeſtlie, otherwiſe, <hi>in vniuerſum priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium amittit, qui conceſſa ſibi abutitur poteſtate:</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he doth loſe all priuiledge that doth abuſe his commiſsion and authoritie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:22"/>
            <p> Let vs goe higher from the Ambaſſadour to his Maiſter the king himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bonifacius de vitallinis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c paſtoralis de re iudicata. verſ. nos tam ex ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritate nu. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> writing vpon the caſe of king <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Sicely</hi> hath theſe wordes. <hi>Si non ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus imperatori, aliquid perpetrat infra fines imperij, ex quo ſi fuiſſet perpetratum per hominem ſubditum impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori, proceſsiſſet crimen laeſae maieſtatis: committit ex hoc illud crimen, quod ratione loci delicti, ſortitur forum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoris, &amp; ſub eius iuriſdictione &amp; poteſtate ex eo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituitur &amp; quoad delictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; quoad qualitatem delicti.</hi> If any perſon being no ſubiect of Themperors, do commit any crime within the limits of Thempire, whereby the ſame beeing committed by one of the Emperors ſubiectes, ſhould amount to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of high treaſon: the ſame doth commit the like crime hereby, which in regarde of the place of the offence is ſubiect to the Emperours autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and he is hereby brought vnder his iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and power both concerning his offence and the qualitie of his offence. And if ſome will yet obiect, that all this may and ought to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode in ſuch perſons as are inferiour and vnder the degree of Kinges and Princes: heare what hee addeth farder in the ſame place,<note place="margin">Bonifacius nu. <hi>72</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rex (inquit) delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendo in imperio efficitur de iuriſdictione imperatoris ratione delicti, &amp; ſic fit ligabilis delinquendo ſicut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahendo.</hi> A King if hee doth offende within the Empire, is made thereby one of the iuriſdiction of the Empire, by reaſon of his offence, and ſo is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable by his delict, as he is by his contract: for elſe this abſurditie would followe and a daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous plague to all Princes, that one king might ſafely kill an other king, and that in his owne
<pb facs="tcp:8764:23"/>kingdome by violence, and the king (whoſe death is ſought) may not for his ſafety put to death ſuch a murdering king by Iuſtice, and by that meanes alſo (as I ſayd before) there ſhoulde bee giuen an occaſion of treacherous dealing, which the lawe abhorreth, and willeth by all meanes to be eſchu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The lawe therefore is generall and reacheth not onely to the Nobilitie and Commons of anie Realme in regarde of ſubiection, but alſo to the forreiner, to the Ambaſſadour, to his Lorde and maſter the King, in reſpect of their coniurations, if any ſuch conſpirators bee apprehended where they within an other kings dominion, haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: for the offence of conſpiracie, doth deueſt &amp; depriue them, and euerie of them of their priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and prerogatiue (if they had any) like as the <hi>ſanctuarie</hi> will ſaue a mans life for <hi>homicide:</hi> but not when <hi>homicide</hi> is committed within the <hi>ſanctuarie,</hi> for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his own fault he doth waue the benefit of all priuiledges and prerogatiue.<note place="margin">L auxilian de miuoribus c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè de electione.</note> 
               <hi>Quia fruſtra le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis auxilium inuocat qui in legem committit.</hi> He doth claime in vaine the benefit of the lawe, that doeth offend againſt the lawe.</p>
            <p>So is the Queenes Maieſtie in her gratious Realme, a <hi>ſanctuarie</hi> to euerie king that commeth within the ſame vnder her highneſſe protection, vntill he committeth a capitall delict and offence againſt the ſame, and than vpon the reaſon of the foreſaid lawes, he looſeth the benefit &amp; priuiledge thereof: like as the benefite or priuiledge of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduit is loſt, when after the ſafe conduit graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, any crime is committed, but for a farder con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the premiſſes we ſhall ſpeake more at large in the next chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſixt Chapter, containing an</hi> aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to certaine obiections latelie made by certaine fauorites of the Queene of Scottes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR aſmuch as ſome partiall and euill affected Aliens, and ſome hollow and diſſembling ſubiects will perhaps in this honourable and iuſt action, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne the proceedings of the whole Parliament, and the ſentence and execution thereuppon, I thinke it not amiſſe to meet with ſome of the beſt of their Arguments, the which at the firſt ſhowe might ſeeme to croſſe or controll their doings.</p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <head>The firſt obiection.</head>
               <p>The firſt obiection is, That <hi>Par in parem non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet imperium,</hi> that is an abſolute Prince ouer and againſt another abſolute Prince hath no iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſoueraintie.</p>
               <p>And this was by Prince <hi>Conradine</hi> a Prince more skilfull in feats of warre, than in points of law,<note place="margin">Collinutius. lib. <hi>4</hi> hiſt. Neapolit.</note> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected vnto <hi>Barius,</hi> king <hi>Charles</hi> his Prothonotarie after that he had read the ſentence of death giuen againſt him.</p>
               <p>The like argument doth <hi>Matheus Pariſienſis</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in king <hi>Iohns</hi> caſe,<note place="margin">Pariſienſis Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachus in ſua hiſtoria.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the French king wold haue ſentenced him for the Dukedome of <hi>Norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</hi> Vpon the which <hi>maxime</hi> or rule it is inferred that foraſmuch as our Queen, &amp; <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> were both Queenes, and of egall power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, that the one can haue no ſuch power to ſentence or puniſh the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Anſweare.</head>
               <p>For aunſwere, it may then trulie and iuſtlie
<pb facs="tcp:8764:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>be ſaid, that whatſoeuer ſhowe this argument ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in apparance, yet it is nothing at all in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>For to let paſſe that (which is much doubted of by many) whether the Scottiſh Queene were, at the time of the ſentence giuen, Queene of <hi>Scotland</hi> or no, ſeeing by the three eſtates of <hi>Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> ſhe was diſabled.</p>
               <p>To omit alſo that ſhee relinquiſhed long time before all her right, title and intereſt in the ſame realme (if ſhe had any) to the Lord <hi>Iemie</hi> her ſonne now king of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To paſſe ouer in like maner how euident a thing it is, and moſt notorious, that the kinges of <hi>Scots</hi> haue been feudataries and done homage vnto the kings of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Hall, and Foxes hiſtorie, <hi>reg.</hi> 4. <hi>William</hi> Conqerour. <hi>malconib. Edward.</hi> 1. <hi>Richard.</hi> 2.</note> and haue appeared in perſon in Parliament at Yorke, and had the place of the firſt Peere in <hi>England,</hi> whereby it may bee inferred that the Scottiſh Queene was no abſolute Queene, but had reſpect &amp; was inferior to the crowne of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> if we ſhould graunt them all this, for diſputi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſake, that ſhee was ſtill Queene of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and farder, that ſhe was an abſolute Queen, what than? what can they infer of this? doth equalitie in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie giue ſupreame power and ſoueraintie in the kindome of <hi>England?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This her ſoueraintie hath vndoubtedly a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie relation to her owne ſubiects the Scots, and kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> not vnto the Engliſh and realme of <hi>England:</hi> &amp; albeit I do grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here for ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb facs="tcp:8764:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſake more than may doe, to wit, that ſhe was ſtill a Queene in dignitie,<note place="margin">Thomas Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticus.</note> yet I may right well deny her to be a Queene in ſoueraintie: for ſhe left all her ſoueraintie behinde her, and became a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſon and no ſoueraine, at what time ſhee came from <hi>Loghléuen</hi> caſtle in <hi>Scotlande,</hi> to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Cokermouth</hi> in <hi>Englande.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this point may ſoone be tryed by ſampling the ſame in an other Princeſſe comming into anie forreine countrey. If the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhould come into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> although perhaps the French King mought take him for his brother, in the ſence of the Poet <hi>(fratrum concordia rara)</hi> yet I doubt he would not take him there for his fellow,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lucan.</hi> Tullie in his booke of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiess.</note> 
                  <hi>Omniſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> potestas impatiens conſortis erit:</hi> there is no kingdome that will abide a Copartner.<note place="margin">D D in l. eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum f. de iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſd. omnium Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum.</note> And (as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaieth) <hi>Nulla ſides nec ſancta ſocietas regni est,</hi> There can be no firme faith, nor holy ſocietie of a kingdome: ouer and aboue that euerie Prince in his owne principalitie is the greater,<note place="margin">c cum inferior de maior. &amp; obed.</note> and it is an infallible rule, that euerie Kinge out of his owne kingdome is no more but a priuate perſon.<note place="margin">Lapus in alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. xcij.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paulus</hi>) <hi>in ſuae prouinciae homines tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm imperium habet, &amp; hoc dum in prouincia eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I. preſes f. de officio preſidis.</note> 
                  <hi>nam ſi exceſſerit priuatus est,</hi> A preſident, hath ſouerainty, onely vppon the ſubiectes of his owne prouince, and that whileſt he is within his prouince, but if he goeth forth of it, he is a priuate perſon.</p>
               <p>Vpon the concluſion of which lawe there grew amongeſt the learned this queſtion,<note place="margin">Baratolus. lib. <hi>12.</hi> de dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus. c.</note> whether a Kinge paſsing thorough, or reſiant in another
<pb facs="tcp:8764:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>kinges Realme and dominion, mought make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his ſubiectes knightes: and ſome helde opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that he could not, for that he had not there <hi>merum imperium,</hi> ſupreme power and ſoueraintie, but <hi>Regiam duntaxat dignitatem,</hi> that is only the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignitie of a king. Other reſolued thus, that albeit in this caſe hee had no ſuch ſoueraintie in him, yet bicauſe this act was not <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentioſae iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionis,</hi> of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentious iuriſdiction as when ſutes paſſe in the kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtory between party &amp; party,<note place="margin">Iaſon &amp; Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander in L. extra territorium de iuriſd. omnium iudicum.</note> but <hi>iuriſdictionis voluntariae,</hi> of a iuriſdiction volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, ſuch as paſſe vpon pleaſure before himſelfe: they were of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he myght make knights, like as one Biſhop may approue willes, and confer orders in the Dioceſſe of another Biſhop, becauſe the ſame is <hi>iuriſdictionis voluntariae,</hi> of a iuriſdiction voluntarie: but that a king in another kings domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or a Biſhop in the dioceſſe of another Biſhop hath <hi>merum imperium,</hi> or ſoueraigntie, that can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſhowne, but the quite contrarie.</p>
               <p>Neither only is euery one in his owne territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie chiefe and greater than an other, who in other reſpects notwithſtanding, is many wayes greater than himſelfe: but alſo he may puniſh there ſuch a perſon greater than himſelf, offending in his terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie inſomuch that an Archbiſhop by a Biſhop in the Biſhops own territory, an Emperor by a king, in a kings dominion and countrie, and a king by a Magiſtrate of a free Citie may there be puniſhed for his offence.</p>
               <p>Neither doth the rule <hi>Par in parem</hi> take anie place in that caſe, and ſo in the caſe of an Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe
<pb facs="tcp:8764:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Panormitan</hi> and <hi>Felin</hi> expreſſely ſet downe,<note place="margin">C cum inſeriors de maior. &amp; obed.</note> that he may by his inferiour Byſhoppe (being not his ſuffragan) receiue condigne puniſhment for the offence, that hee hath committed within the ſayde Byſhoppes dioceſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anchoranus</hi> addeth farder,<note place="margin">Anchoran clem. <hi>1.</hi> de fore compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rente.</note> that if a patriarche ſhould offende within the territorie of <hi>Bononie,</hi> the Byſhop there mought puniſh him accordingly.</p>
               <p>And that an Emperour may be in like manner puniſhed by an other Prince, in whoſe territorie he hath offended,<note place="margin">Vaſkins lib. <hi>1.</hi> contr. f. illuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium.</note> 
                  <hi>Ferdinandus Vaskins</hi> in his booke of princely controuerſies doeth affirme in theſe wordes: <hi>Imperatorem ab alio principe in cuius territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio deliquiſset, puniri poſſe non dubitauerim.</hi> And that a Magiſtrate in like maner of a free Citie may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh a king offending within the territorie of the Citie, we reade examples in ſundrye hiſtories, as howe <hi>Iustinian</hi> a king,<note place="margin">Functius in cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologia.</note> was put to death by <hi>Helias</hi> a patrician, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon of the premiſſes, is grounded vpon two concluſions of the lawe. The one is that the Emperour, the King, the Archbiſhoppe, and the Biſhoppe, are out of their owne kingdomes, countryes, and dioceſſe, but as priuate perſons, The other that euerie Prince and ruler within his own kingdome and rule is greater than any other, although hee were the greateſt monarche in the worlde.</p>
               <p>The which a great learned man called <hi>Lapus de caſtello,</hi> in plaine words moſt apparantly ſhoweth,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>his wordes be theſe:<note place="margin">Lapus de caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo alleg. <hi>91.</hi> nu. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Extra territorium ſuum quili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet Rex cenſetur ad inſtar priuati, &amp; conſtat, quòd v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſquiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in ſuo territorio maior est: vndè populus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis in ſuo territorio magis poteſt, quàm Dominus Rex illuſtriſsimus &amp; perpetuus Anglorum,</hi> Euerie kinge out of his owne kingdome is accompted as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſon, and it is apparant that euerie perſon in his owne territorie is the greater. And therefore the people of <hi>Senes</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> can in their owne ſtate and territorie, doe more than the mightie and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Lord the King of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, we may further ſhew in this caſe that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhee were a Queen and by her royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue not to be touched, yet if ſhe doth deueſt herſelfe of her prerogatiue or make herſelfe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the iuriſdiction of another, than can ſhe not claime her priuiledge nor exempt her ſelfe from the others iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as <hi>Vlpian praefectus praeto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Emperor, ſaith: <hi>Eſt receptum eo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iure vtimur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. <hi>14.</hi> ff. de iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iud.</note> 
                  <hi>vt ſi quis maior, vel aequalis ſubijciat ſe iuriſdictioni alterius poſsit ei &amp; aduerſus eum ius dici.</hi> It is receiued, and is a lawe which wee haue daily in vre, that if the greater or egall doe ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto the iuriſdiction of an other, the lawe may there bee miniſtred to him and againſt him, vpon which law <hi>Paulus Caſtrenſis, Iaſon</hi> &amp; diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do note that there are two kinds of ſubmiſsion, <hi>Expreſſa &amp; tacita:</hi> expreſſe commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by giuing open conſent: ſecrete ſubmiſsion by making any contract or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting any offence: &amp; ſo within their territories. <hi>Vnus Princeps vel Baro poteſt alium principe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vel Conbarone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> punire.</hi> One Prince or Baron may puniſh an other prince or Baron.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Than ſince the Scottiſh Queene in her Maieſties Realme againſt her Maieſtie, not of ignorance, but wittinglie deſirous of her crowne, hath offended, and that in no leſſe caſe than the caſe of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by her treaſonable fact: ſhee hath yeelded a ſecrete ſubmiſsion to the iuriſdiction of <hi>Englande,</hi> and therefore there rightfullie to bee puniſhed by law.</p>
               <p>Wherfore to conclude, ſince ſome doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhee were a Queen (as which had reſigned vp and thereby had no kingdome) ſince, if ſhee were a Queene in dignitie, yet in ſoueraintie ſhe was no Queene, but a priuate perſon comming into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes dominion, ſince euerie Prince in his owne kingdome is chiefeſt, and other there are inferiour to him, ſince an inferiour perſon may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his ſuperiours for ſuch offences they commit within his iuriſdiction, ſince a Prince by offending ſubmitteth himſelfe to the ſtate of that countrie where he offendeth, and may haue the law paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him for it: This obiection of <hi>Par in parem</hi> little ſerueth their purpoſe, as which is to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of facts committed in their ſeueral king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms &amp; territories. For than may not the queene of <hi>England</hi> puniſh her for ought ſhee hath done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in <hi>Scotland,</hi> becauſe they are in this caſe <hi>Pares,</hi> that is, of egall authoritie, but for her demerites in <hi>England</hi> (where they are not <hi>Pares</hi>) but the Queene of <hi>Scots</hi> inferiour to the Queene of <hi>England,</hi> there the queene of <hi>England</hi> reteineth only the ſupreme ſoueraintie, and therefore there may notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſaid obiection, lawfully ſentence the <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> queene.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:27"/>
               <head>The <hi>2.</hi> Obiection.</head>
               <p>AN other obiection is made thus: The <hi>Scottiſh</hi> queene purſued by her owne ſubiects fled into the realme of <hi>England</hi> as a ſuppliant for ſuccour, and therfore of common curteſie ſhe ought to be well entreated there, nor to be deteined as a priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or if ſhe were deteined yet to haue the libertie to be put vnto her raunſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>TO this may be anſwered, firſt that euerie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon paſsing through or reſiaunt in another kingdome, without a ſafe conduct or paſport be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not in amitie or league with the other is a lawfull priſoner in the ſame. And therefore in all the leagues that we make with the houſe of <hi>Burgu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> or kingdome of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> or they with vs, there is an expreſſe article or capitulation ſet downe, <hi>vt ſit amicitia foedus &amp; pax, &amp; vt liceat per dulces aquas &amp;c. commeare,</hi> that there bee an amitie, league, and peace: and that it may be lawfull for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to paſſe by water or land through the realme freely and without impeachment.</p>
               <p>Which being graunted, than muſt we farther in this caſe conſider, howe that vntill the laſt yeare there neuer was <hi>Foedus vel pax inita,</hi> any league or peace made beween <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Englande,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ceſsatio à billo,</hi> an abſtinence from the warres, whereby the Scottiſh Queene comming into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8764:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>could not challenge any libertie or freedome within that kingdome.</p>
               <p>Than the law ſtanding thus that no man <hi>Niſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federatus retinet ſibi libertate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in aliquo regno &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. non dubite ff. de captiuis.</note> No man can reteyne liberty in an other kyngdome without he be in league, &amp; confederated with the king, or come into the realme by ſafe conduct: I thinke it will not be gaine-ſaid, but ſhe was ſtaide here and deteined lawfully.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is not heere to be paſt ouer in ſilence, how the Queene of Scots vſurped the ſtile and armes of the crowne of <hi>England,</hi> a thing moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious to the whole worlde.</p>
               <p>Since therefore ſhee was a Competitor of the crowne, and thirſted after the crown of this realm in poſſeſsion, &amp; could not bee reclaimed from the ſame, although by her Ambaſſadors ſhe promiſed diuers times to doe it: ſince God had put her into her Maieſties hands, well might her Maieſtie take and keepe her vntill ſhe had perfourmed her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
               <p>For did not <hi>Tiberius</hi> deteine king <hi>Cotys?</hi> did not <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor, doe ſo with the Emperor <hi>Licinius?</hi> Dyd not <hi>Lewes</hi> the French kyng, called <hi>Lewes</hi> the Pitiefull, doe the like vnto <hi>Barnard</hi> king of <hi>Italy?</hi> Doth it not ſtand with the law of nature, which is (<hi>ius immutabile,</hi> a law immutable) for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie perſon to prouide for the ſaftie of himſelfe, and all that are committed vnto his charge?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And if we ſhould graunt her, that ſhe came in as a ſuppliant, and of free will, and not dryuen in by tempeſt, when ſhe meant (according to ſome wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) to haue gone into Fraunce: what if ſhe came hither for ſuccour? (as it may be whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſaw no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedie ſhe ſhewed to be her intent) is it not as great or more reaſon for our ſoueraigne to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour her ſelfe as to ſuccour her?</p>
               <p>For if the Scottiſh queene thinketh our queene bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by the law of nations, to take her after this maner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into her protection: doth not the law of nature teache our queene vnder colour of protection to prouide againſt prodition?</p>
               <p>So that whiles the other carried alwayes with her this ambitious minde, to bereaue the queene our ſoueraigne of her kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> if ſhe had been ſet at liberty, had ſhe not been far more enabled to accompliſh her deſſeines? for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to what intent dyd the princes and her allies, and all her adherents deſire, and thirſt ſo much her enlargement, but to make her an head to be ſet vp in time of inuaſion againſt her Maieſtie?</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing that her Maieſtie had no iuſt cauſe of her ſo doing and her deteyning heere, had beene wholly vnlawful, mought ſhe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeke to take away the life from the queene of <hi>Englande?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The practiſe of ſo many horrible treaſons, may not be ſhifted with this ſo vntrue and ſlight pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, nor coloured with a faire ſhowe of natures
<pb facs="tcp:8764:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>lawe: for ſo many ſeditious vnnatural and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſſeinmentes moſt repugnant to the lawe of nature, and contrarie to the lawes both of God and man, can not abide any ſuch ſhift or colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="objection">
               <head>The <hi>3.</hi> Obiection.</head>
               <p>THe two firſt obiections made againſt the ſayde honorable ſentence, are in regarde of the Queene of <hi>Scottes</hi> perſon: But the two obiections following, doe rather tende to the diſalowance of the lawe, whereupon the ſentence is grounded. For (ſay they) although wee ſhould graunt that one king may ſentence an other king delinquent and reſident within his kingdome, wee thinke it not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenable that in the caſe of a king, the tryal ſhoulde be by the municipall and ſtatute lawe of the lande, but only by the common and generall lawe receiued amongeſt all other nations.</p>
               <p>Againe ſince the lawe of Nations (as they ſay) puniſh the effect and not the affect: him that hath committed, not him that willeth or intendeth treaſon, that therefore they haue delt iniuriouſly with the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> queen in puniſhing her by death, for onely willing and intending treaſon, which as yet had not the intended effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The aunſwere.</head>
               <p>FOr anſwere to the firſt of theſe two obiections. A Prince may bee tried by the municipall and ſtatute lawe of the lande, where he offendeth, the
<pb facs="tcp:8764:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>which appeareth by one of the moſt auncient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of the Ciuill law <hi>Albericus de Roſate,</hi> and that in the caſe of a king ſentenced for high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Albericus L quiſquis ad L Iuliam maieſt. C D D in L <hi>1.</hi> c de trinitate.</note> where he moueth this ſaid caſe, and reſolueth it thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nonne vnuſquiſque delinquens iudicabitur ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm leges loci in quo deliquit? Reſpondeo, verum eſt, ſi de intentione legiſlatoris fuit, factum ipſum afficere &amp; omnem perſonam quae incideret in ipſum factum, Nam non plus extenditur lex quàm fuit de intentione legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris:</hi> That is to ſay, Is not this agreed for law, that euerie delinquent or offendor againſt the law, ſhal be adiudged according to the lawes of the place where he committed his delict or offence? That is true, (ſaith hee) if it were the minde and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the maker of the lawe, to puniſh that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and euerie perſon that ſhoulde fall within the compaſſe of the ſayde offence, for the lawe is neuer extended farder than the intention of the lawe maker.</p>
               <p>And was not the intention of the makers of the ſtatute lawe, made the 27 of her Maieſties raigne, moſt euident after ſo many ſeditious deſſeignme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and moſt wicked plots laide both for the indaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of her highneſſe moſt royall perſon, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the ruine of the common weale, to deuiſe a ſpeedie remedie for ſuch an apparant miſchiefe? Did not the wicked attempts of <hi>Throgmorton</hi> and <hi>Parie,</hi> and the continuall practiſe of fugitiues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the ſeas, and traiterous ſubiectes at home, make it as cleare as the ſunne in the eye and heart of euerie good ſubiect, howe neceſſarie it was to prouide ſpeedie remedie herein? Did not (vpon
<pb facs="tcp:8764:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe reſpectes, and to meete with theſe and ſuch like miſchiefes) the whole Realme aſſembled in Parliament enact thus:</p>
               <p>That if anie open invaſion or rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be made, in, or vvithin her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Realme, or dominions, or any acte attempted tending to the hurt of her Maieſties moſt royall perſon, by or for any perſon that ſhould or might pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende anye title to the crovvne of this Realme, after her Maieſties deceaſe, or if any thing should be compaſſed or i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined tending to the hurt of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties royall perſon, by anye perſon or vvith the preuitie of any perſon, that shall or may pretend title to the crovvne of this Realme: that then, ſuch perſon vvhatſoeuer should be vvithin the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of that lavve. Wherefore by that lavve (as may bee gathered both by the preamble and body of the act) the ſaide tvvo great daungers vvere ſought to be prouided for, her Maieſties preſeruation and the common peace of thole realm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You will ſay it tended onely to ſubiectes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To that I aunſwere, it had beene then a neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:8764:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>lawe, for thoſe attemptes by ſubiectes by the common lawes of this Realme, and ſo agnized by the ſtatute of 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>de proditionibus,</hi> were high treaſon before, and therefore there needed no new lawe for them.</p>
               <p>For whom was this lawe then eſpecially made? It plainely appeareth by that which is before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, that it eſpecially reſpecteth all thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whomſoeuer, that ſhould or might pretende title to the imperiall crowne of this Realme. And did not <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Scotlande</hi> at, (and long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) the making of that act, pretende title to the crowne of this Realme, not onely to haue it after her Maieſties deceaſe, but foorthwith to be put in actuall poſſeſsion? And did not the ſaide <hi>Marie</hi> after the making of the ſaide ſtatute by her ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and letters, ſpecially addreſſed from her to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, allow and giue her aſſent to the ſame? Neuertheleſſe after the making of this acte, and her ſayde conſent giuen therunto, the monſtrous conſpiracie of <hi>Babington,</hi> by her priuie conſent, and promiſe of rewarde for the murdering of her Maieſties ſacred perſon, and atcheiuing the crowne and diademe in full poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, was practiſed and miraculouſly diſcouered. Which I neede not heere particularly to deduce, ſince there was a moſt honorable ſentence giuen thereof by the moſt part, and the moſt auncienteſt of the nobilitie, ſince their proceedinges were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the whole body of the Realme aſſembled in Parliament, &amp; of them receiued all allowance: ſince both the houſes often ſued vnto her Maieſty, that according to lawe, iuſtice might be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
<pb facs="tcp:8764:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſince her highneſſe at the great intreatie of her ſubiects, ſuffered the ſentence by Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be publiſhed, it plainly appeareth that the intention of the lawe makers, was, that the lawe ſhould reach vnto the Queene of Scots, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie other perſon whoſoeuer being a Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the kingdome. Wherefore it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that although this is ſtatute law, yet ſince it was the minde and intent of the makers that this lawe ſhoulde reache to the Queene of <hi>Scots,</hi> that by offending ſhe is made ſubiect vnto it. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſtatute lawe heerein repugnant in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the lawe of Nations, howbeit, there bee ſome difference in ſome matter of circumſtaunce: but the ſame agreeth with the lawes both ciuill, &amp; of Nations in ſubſtance, which generally do inflict the penaltie of death vpon euery one, that is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of treaſon.</p>
               <p>Beſides, if the ſtatute lawes of <hi>England</hi> wil bind the king himſelf for any matter within his realme when the intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the makers of the law is ſuch (as it is verie plaine and cleere without all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, that it doth) ſhall not a ſtatute law bind the queene of <hi>Scots,</hi> eſpecially for mattter perpetrated within the realme.</p>
               <p>And as touching the ſaid ſtatute of the 27. ſhee could not pretend ignorance, for that ſhe had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of it: nor alledge a miſlike therof, for that by her voluntarie ſubſcription, ſhe had appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it: nor except againſt the ſeueritie of the law, becauſe it is agreeable both to the ciuill law of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> &amp; alſo to the law &amp; cuſtome of her owne
<pb facs="tcp:8764:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>countrie: and therefore it may be ſaid to her, <hi>Non poteſt quis improbare quod ipſe approbauit,</hi> a man may not bee contrary to himſelfe in diſalowing that which himſelfe hath allowed.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Patere legem. quam ipſe tuleris,</hi> ſuffer the ſame lawe which you haue made your ſelfe. Shee meant death to the queene of <hi>Englands</hi> perſon, let her not therefore miſlike if the queene of <hi>England</hi> doth miniſter the like meaſure to her perſon: for as it hath been neere fifteene hundred yeeres agoe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie written:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non est lex aequior vlla,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quàm necis artifices arte perire ſua.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No iuſter lavv can reaſon craue</l>
                  <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeking death, the ſame to haue.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Alſo it is a rule of the ciuill law grounded vpon the law of nature: <hi>Id debet cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> placere in ſua perſona quod placuerit in aliena,</hi> that euerie man ought to like that in his own perſon, which he would haue done in the perſon of another: neither doth the priuiledge of dignity in the perſon alter the nature and qualitie of the offence in caſe of treaſon, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it doth in other caſes, as before I haue ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie wayes confirmed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="objection">
               <head>The <hi>4.</hi> obiection.</head>
               <p>THE fourth obiection made againſt the ſentence and excution of the Scottiſh queene is another
<pb facs="tcp:8764:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>exception taken againſt the law of the lande, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the caſe of treaſon it puniſheth as ſeuerelie the intent as the deede, the minde in conſpiring as the hand in executing: for thus they reaſon.</p>
               <p>It is both againſt the lawe of nations and the law of nature, howſoeuer it bee according to the lawe of your lande to put a queene to death for a bare and naked intent, an imagined treaſon, be it neuer ſo haynous, when there followeth no hurt. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her deſſeines, neither did nor could hurt the Queene of <hi>England,</hi> as neuer hauing their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended effect: what reaſon is it to puniſhe a fancie and feare of treaſon with ſo great a puniſhment as death?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Aunſwere.</head>
               <p>TO this, I make this aunſwere, that the lawe of <hi>England,</hi> heerein inflicteth none other puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for treaſon, than the ciuill law and law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions throughout the whole world, commandeth, vſeth, and practiſeth.</p>
               <p>The ciuill law hath theſe wordes, <hi>Eadem ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate voluntatem ſceleru quae effectum puniri iura volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. quiſquis C. ad L. Iuliam. maieſtatis.</note> the lawes will haue him that conſpireth trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to be puniſhed with the ſame ſeueritie as him that doth commit it.</p>
               <p>Againe, not onlie in the caſe of high treaſon, but alſo <hi>in omnibus atrocioribus delictis punitur affectus, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſequatur effectus,</hi> in al criminal offences of the higheſt degree, the affect is puniſhed, although no
<pb facs="tcp:8764:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>effect follow. And this lawe hath not only been ſo obſerued generally in all nations aboue twelue hundred yeeres paſt: but there was many hundred yeeres before Chriſtes time, <hi>in caſu perduellionis,</hi> in the caſe of treaſon committed againſt the ſtate, the like law called (<hi>lex</hi> 12 <hi>tabularum</hi>) eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>12.</hi> Tabularum ff. ad L. Iuliam. maieſtatis.</note> which inflicteth death for the will and intent of treaſon. And therefore the ſaid two Emperors <hi>Arcadius</hi> &amp; <hi>Honorius</hi> in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution made againſt treaſon, ſaid not <hi>volumus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D. L. quiſquis ad L. Iuliam.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed ſic iura voluerunt,</hi> the lawes were ſo before their time.</p>
               <p>But to ſay that there ought, in offences of the higheſt degree no puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to enſue, vnles the act were conſummate: were moſt againſt law, for two ſpeciall cauſes. The one for that ſuch hope of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitie would encourage malefactors to practiſe moſt daungerous and audacious attempts againſt kinges and common weales. Secondly if they ſtay to puniſh till the fact be done, the loſſe will be ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recuperable: and the offence, as this caſe is in a competitor (though moſt haynous) diſpuniſhable. For in this caſe in queſtion, the death of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie (whom God euer preſerue) being taken away, all commiſsions and magiſtracies for iudicial pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould ceaſe: ſo that this being contriued by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petitor to the kingdome, (as the Queen of Scots by open and expreſſe accord hath often declared herſelfe) the ſame offence by the acceſſe or taking vpon her the crowne and dignitie ſhould by lawe be purged and the competitor cleared.</p>
               <p>For king <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixt, after the ouerthrowe giuen him by king <hi>Edwarde</hi> the fourth, was by act
<pb facs="tcp:8764:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Parliament diſabled from his crowne and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. And yet afterwardes, the ſaide king in his redemption helde Parliament, and in the ſame the queſtion did growe, whether there needed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reuerſall of the ſaide former acte made againſt the ſayde king. It was reſolued that no reuerſall was needfull, but <hi>ipſo facto</hi> that the ſayd king <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the vj. tooke vpon him the royall dignity to be king, whether it were <hi>de iure</hi> or <hi>de facto</hi> that all the fame was voyde.</p>
               <p>The like came in queſtion in the firſt yeare of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the vij. at the firſt Parliament, by him holden: and receiued the ſame reſolution. For the place doth ſo dignifie the perſon, that all ſteine of former actes, is cleane waſhed awaye: and ſo the Queene of <hi>Scottes,</hi> if ſhee might haue brought her practiſes to execution ment, (as theſe pleaders or rather plodders, about <hi>delictum conſummatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> mean) to haue eſcaped vnpuniſhed.</p>
               <p>Seeing than the lawe of <hi>England</hi> in caſe of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is no other than <hi>Lex per omnes gentes diffuſa,</hi> the lawe ſpredde abroade through out all Nations, by the which generally all the Nations of the worlde are gouerned, kinges obeyed, offences puniſhed: I thinke it appeareth to anie indifferent Reader, vnto howe broken a ſtaffe they leane, that cite the lawe of Nations againſt vs.</p>
               <p>And whereas they adde farder that the lawe of Nature maketh for the Scottiſh Queene in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe: I take that obiection farther out of ſquare than the other.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Of this lawe <hi>Tullie</hi> writeth very grauely in his booke of common wealth in this wiſe:<note place="margin">Cicero. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de republica.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſt verò lex recta ratio, naturae congruens, diffuſa in omnes, conſtans, ſempiterna, quae vocet ad officium iubendo, vetando à fraude deterreat.</hi> There is a lawe which is reaſon it ſelfe, agreeable to Nature, imprinted in the hearts of all, alwayes one and the ſame, and wherof there is no ende, which putteth euerie man in minde to doe his dutie by commaunding, and withholdeth euerie man from doing wrong by forbidding.</p>
               <p>Nowe is this <hi>Recta ratio</hi> to practiſe a Princeſſe death,<note place="margin">Rectaratio.</note> &amp; for a kingdome, to thirſt after the bloud of an innocent? If this be no reaſon, but a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell reaſonleſſe: then what is more agreeable to reaſon than this, that the Scottiſh Queene ſhould haue that done to her, which ſhee meant to haue done to our Soueraigne.</p>
               <p>And what is more diſagreeable to reaſon, than that the Prince ſhould not puniſh the intent of a Traitour, vntill hee had murdered the prince, and brought his wicked purpoſe to effect? Is there any thing more abſurde and vnconſonant to reaſon, than for a kinge ſtill to ſpare the Conſpirator till the Conſpirator hath made away the king?</p>
               <p>Neither is this <hi>naturae congruens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Naturae congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens.</note> agreeable to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for a Prince to incite, to counſell, to promiſe a reward vnto ſubiects to kill their owne liege La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and Soueraigne.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Florentinus</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinus L. vt vini de inſtit. &amp; iure ff.</note> that <hi>cùm natura cognatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quandam inter homines conſtituerit, hominem homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
<pb facs="tcp:8764:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>inſidiari nefas eſt:</hi> ſeeing nature hath conioyned men in a certaine kindred, it is nefarious for one man to deſtroy another. And as this is vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and monſtrous for a man to compaſſe the death of his brother: ſo this is contrary and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to nature, for a man by all poſsible meanes not to defende himſelfe. For as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Cicero pro Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſt haec non ſcripta ſed nata lex: quam non didicimus, accepimus, degimus, veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex natura ipſa arripuimus, hauſimus, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsimus: ad qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> docti ſed facti, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtituti ſed imbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſumus: vt ſi vita noſtra in aliquas inſidias, ſi in vim at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in tela aut latronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aut inimicoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incidiſſet, omnis honeſtae ratio eſſet expediendae ſalutis:</hi> There is a law (ſaith he) not written for vs, but borne with vs: which wee haue not learned, receiued, or read of other, but which wee haue taken, drawen, and wreſted from nature herſelfe: vnto which wee are not taught by other, but borne by nature, not inſtructed, but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally inclined: that if our life ſhall fall into anie danger, violence, or weapons of theeues or ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in that caſe euerie meanes to ſaue and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour our ſelues, is both honeſt and commendable. <hi>Silent enim leges inter arma, nec ſe expectari iubent, cùm ei qui expectare velit, iniuſta poena luendae ſit, quàm iuſta repetenda:</hi> For the lawes are ſilent among princes weapons: neither do command, that they ſhould be regarded, when he that hath regard vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them muſt abide ſome vniuſt puniſhment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that any good meanes by them can be had to puniſhe the offendor. And not onelie this (to defend himſelf) is according to nature, but this is alſo, to cut off euils in the firſt ſpring, leaſt by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance they grow ſo ſtrong, that hereafter, when men would, they cannot remedie them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Further is added by <hi>Tullie:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diffuſa in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> 
                  <hi>Diffuſa in omnes,</hi> that it is generallie receiued of all nations: <hi>Constans,</hi> that is conſtant,<note place="margin">Conſtans.</note> alwaies one and the ſame, not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable either in reſpect of perſon, place, or time, but to all perſons, and in all places, and times it is one, the ſame, and like it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sempiternall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sempi terna. Quae vocet ad officiu m iuben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, veiando, <hi>à</hi> fraude deterreat</note> which hath been from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſhal continue the ſame to all ſucceeding ages that ſhall come hereafter, whoſe propertie is inwardly to ſpeake to a mans heart ſhewing what hee ſhould followe, and what he ſhould forſake.</p>
               <p>Now had the Scottiſh queene this warrant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature? and did nature teach her to kill her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector? Or if her nature did ſo inſtruct her, is this the conſcience of all other? and are theſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires of good mens heartes? hath this been the practiſe of natures lawe, which hath been from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, and is alway to continue?</p>
               <p>Nay ſince the lawe of Nature is imprinted in the hart of man, and there ſheweth what he ſhould will, or what he ſhould intende: whoſoeuer doth not ſo will and ſo intend to doe, as this law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, he is not to be accounted an obſeruer but a breaker of the lawe. And therefore for them to appeale to the lawe of Nature, for excuſe of their euill purpoſe or dooing, is eyther to make Nature repugnant to her ſelfe, or to giue ſentence againſt them for their euill intente.</p>
               <p>Wherefore as theſe properties of the Lawe of Nature nothing make for the Scottiſh Queen, but
<pb facs="tcp:8764:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>are wholely abhorrent from her endeuours: (for who dare ſay that ſuch her complots are approue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by nature) ſo they are a great warrant to her Maieſtie, when there is no meanes left to ſaue both, than by the others death to prouide for the ſafetie of her owne perſon and her Realme. For this Nature teacheth, and the conſcience within, better than a thouſande witneſſes doeth warrant, this hath beene the guiſe of all Nations, other Princes haue doone it before, and they that doe come after will doe the ſame.</p>
               <p>And as the will that willeth treaſon is therfore culpable, becauſe it ſo willeth: ſo is it likewiſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable if it bee knowne. But in this caſe of the Scottiſh Queene, there was not onely treaſon in her will, and in her ſecrete intent, (a thing much repugnant to the good inſtinct of Nature) but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo her intent was communicated vnto other, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded on with other. And howbeit ſhee failed of her mayne purpoſe, which was to haue her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie killed, the lande ouerrunned, and her ſelfe to be poſſeſſed of the crowne: yet ſhe had her forth in many her deſſeinmentes, as the rebellion in the North, the confederacie of forrein Princes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade the land, the coniuration of natural Engliſh, moſt vnnaturally to deſtroy their own Soueraine, and many other.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſince the will and intent in haynous faultes, by Ciuill lawe is to be puniſhed by death, and nature likewiſe reproueth and puniſheth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vniuſt thought, ſince the other did ſtill wil and ingeminate her treaſons, and ſtill would if ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:8764:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>could bring it to effect, ſince in this her caſe, there is not onely her will to deſire treaſon, but her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouement to allowe, and promiſe to rewarde the ſame, accompanied with many other ſeditious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes: who can ſay that ſo to will, deſerueth not death, although the will lacketh both force and forth, and bringeth not all that is conſpired to effect.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>That in two eſpeciall caſes, the <hi>drawing of the ſworde of one</hi> Prince againſt an other, is not only lawfull, but neceſſarie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the perſons of Princes are moſt ſacred, and the maieſtie of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute king very reuerende, as beeing the Lordes annoynted, aduaunced by him to their imperiall crownes and dignities, in ſuch ſort as it behoueth euerie man reuerently to ſpeake of them, and in al dutifull ſort to demeane themſelues towardes them: yet ſince there be euil Princes aſwell as good, ſuch which haue made themſelues vnworthy to rule, whome God hath thruſt from their crowne: it is not amiſſe for the contentment of other, (if ſo be there be anye ſo euill, that is therewith diſcontented) to prooue vnto them, howe lawefull it is in theſe two caſes,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>for one abſolute Prince to drawe his ſworde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an other. And that is, firſt, where the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſon of a Prince, is by another Princes means endaungered of life: that then and in this caſe, he may redeeme his own life and ſafetie, by the death and deſtruction of that other.</p>
            <p>Secondly, where not the life of the Prince, but the diſturbance of the publike weale, the ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſtate is intended and ſought for, and likely without this laſt remedie to enſue: In this caſe to ſaue his countrey, and people, whom God hath commited to his charge, a Prince may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſentence the abfoluteſt Monarche in the worlde.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, I take it aſwell by the learned in the lawe of God as by thoſe of the lawe Ciuill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of, that <hi>Charitas incipit à ſe,</hi> charitie or loue beginneth at it ſelfe: vnto which accordeth that which <hi>Florentinus</hi> writeth <hi>quod quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ob tutelam cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſui facit, hoc iure feciſſe exiſtimatur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">L <hi>3.</hi> de iuſtitia &amp; iure.</note> That which euerie man doeth for the ſafegarde of his perſon, he is deemed to haue doone it lawfully. The which <hi>Tullie</hi> in theſe wordes farther ſheweth:<note place="margin">Cicero pro Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</note> 
               <hi>hoc &amp; ratio doctis, &amp; neceſsitas barbaris, &amp; mos gentibus, &amp; feris natura ipſa praeſcripſit: vt omnem ſemper vim quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ope poſſent, à corpore, à capite, à vita ſua propulſarent.</hi> This both reaſon hath taught the learned, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie the ignorant, and cuſtome all Nations, and nature it ſelfe the wilde and ſauage beaſtes: that they ſhould by all meanes poſsible, preſerue their liues from all violence.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The which being graunted,<note place="margin">1. caſe lawefull for one king to draw his ſword againſt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when his life is endaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered.</note> then where a Prince hath no meanes left him, by the euill and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous practiſes of that other, to ſaue his owne life, but this one: in this caſe he may rewarde the other according to the wickedneſſe of his wayes, giue the others life a ranſome for his owne, and bring that due death on him, which vniuſtly hee had thought to haue inflicted on an other. For ſince nature and wiſedome teacheth this, if ſo be there fall out ſo deſperate a caſe of two euils, to chuſe the leaſt: when one cannot as hee would, to doe then (as he may) that which maketh for the beſt: what ſhould a Prince in this caſe doe? ſhould hee ſuffer himſelfe vniuſtly to be murdered as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent? or ſhould he iuſtly drawe out his ſworde againſt the nocent? Let a man, let a Prince, make this caſe his caſe, and ſay, what would he? would he betray his owne guiltleſſe bloud, and ſuffer the wicked to haue his forth? would he ſtill lye at the warde, and neuer ſtrike, being ſo often aſſaulted? If ſo be there be one found ſo voyde of reaſon, ſo careleſſe of himſelfe, yet is not God delighted therewith: for hee would haue vs to preuent the occaſions of greater euill, and to puniſh the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for their ſinnes. For be hee the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the worlde, yet God neither liketh nor approueth folly in him, neither would he haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to be a furtherer of him in his ſinne.</p>
            <p>And doe not Princes ſinne in compaſsing the death of other innocent and harmeleſſe princes?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> in his boke of duties.</note> As God abhorreth this fact in them, ſo he diſliketh all them that further it, all that will not hinder it. For as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, he that hindereth not euil when
<pb facs="tcp:8764:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>he may, is aſwell in fault as he that did it.</p>
            <p>May then Princes puniſh treaſonable facts, and will they ſuffer them vnpuniſhed, when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe attempted, and likely to effect their intended purpoſe? if they doe thus ſuffer, they doe not hinder but further treaſon: &amp; are in a ſort guiltie (if after they miſcarrie) of their owne death. For if they had puniſhed them for the firſt attempts, they had freed themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the ſecond: but by winking at, and pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the firſt, they themſelues are in cauſe of their after miſfortune. Which if it ſhould follow, that an ouer mercifull Prince ſhould bee murdered by his Competitor whom he ſpared: whether had it been better in it ſelfe, or more allowable by the lawes of God &amp; man that a wicked Prince which had often practiſed, and at length hath compaſſed the death of another, ſhoulde firſt himſelfe haue been put to death, than that an innocent &amp; harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Prince ſhould by the villanous practiſe of that other, be traiterouſlie flaine? Surely iuſtice &amp; ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce will ſoone make aunſweare, and teach vs what aunſwere in this caſe we ſhould make. For what is more abſurde, than that the Prince ſhould ſtay from taking away the Conſpirator till the Conſpirator hath taken away the Prince? Or who is there that ſhould think that the law in this caſe doth not account euen in a Prince, <hi>voluntatem pro facto,</hi> the verie intention, for the act, where <hi>poſt factum,</hi> that is, after the deede done, and the prince flaine, there is neither lawe nor magiſtrate remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>Neither is this without many notable preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents:<note place="margin">Cicero pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ege Deiotaro.</note> for when <hi>Tully</hi> pleaded for <hi>Deiotarus</hi> king of
<pb facs="tcp:8764:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Gallograecia,</hi> he was ſo far from vrgeing or ſtanding on the preheminence &amp; prerogatiue of a king, that he confeſſed, if <hi>Caſtor</hi> the kings nephew could haue iuſtified his accuſation, to wit, that the ſaide king had gone about to make warre on <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie waies to haue conſpired againſt his perſon: that than hee was worthie to ſuffer death,<note place="margin">Cicero Orat. pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rege Deiotaro.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt (inquit) iniquum in tuo duntaxat periculo, Caeſar, vt rex reus capitis arguatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not vnlawful for a king to be arraigned of life &amp; death.</note> if thy life, O <hi>Caeſar</hi> be ſhot at, &amp; endaungered, than is it not an vnlawfull thing for a king to be arraigned of life and death.</p>
            <p>In like maner all the Doctors of the law in both the kingdomes of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicelie</hi> beeing aſked their iudgement by king <hi>Charles</hi> aforeſaid,<note place="margin">The opinion of the learned in <hi>Italie</hi> in this caſe.</note> what by law hee might doe with king <hi>Conradine</hi> his priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:<note place="margin">Collinutiue. li <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> they gaue this their ſentence for law, that hee might lawfully put him to death.</p>
            <p>Neither was this the iudgement of the lawyers alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Henricus Gilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingenſis in hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Auſtriaca.</hi> A popes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this caſe.</note> but it was by Pope Clement the 4. when he was in the ſame caſe conſulted, aunſwered, <hi>in vita Conradini mors Caroli, mors Caroli vita Conradini,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collinutius. li.</hi> 4. The articles of treaſon laid to king <hi>Conra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines</hi> charge, &amp; comprehended in the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Note the verie ſame caſe of ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt the Scottiſh queene, as was againſt <hi>Conra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine.</hi>
               </note> the life of <hi>Conradine</hi> is <hi>Charles</hi> death, and the death of <hi>Charles,</hi> is the life of <hi>Conradine.</hi> whereupon there enſued a ſolemne ſentence againſt the ſaide <hi>Conradine</hi> in theſe wordes, <hi>Quia Conradinus eccleſiae pacem perturbauit, Regiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nomen falsò ſibi adſumpſit &amp; regi mortem intentauit: morte damnamus,</hi> bicauſe <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radine</hi> hath troubled the peace of the Church, and vniuſtly hath taken on him the name and title of the king and conſpired his death: wee condemne him to die.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The like cauſe moued the vertuous and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great,<note place="margin">Euſebius, Mex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ia, Socraies, &amp; a lij.</note> to put firſt <hi>Maximinianus</hi> the emperor, whoſe daughter he had married, and after that, <hi>Licinius</hi> the Emperour his brother in law to death; and ſo by the death of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to purchaſe the ſafetie of himſelfe: neither ought this to moue a diſdaine of the puniſher,<note place="margin">Non me paena dolet, ſed me ruiſſe doles.</note> or pitie towardes the puniſhed in other Princes hearts. For if euill kings be not aſhamed to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe and compaſſe the death of kings and princes, their equals in dignitie: what reaſon haue good kings to pitie ſuch ſhameleſſe princes, when they are iuſtly puniſhed for their demerites?<note place="margin">That which thou approueſt in thy ſelf, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like not in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other</note> ſince they haue diſgraced their princely order conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their equals, and made themſelues vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to raigne, and vnworthie to liue.</p>
            <p>Nay what prince would not commend &amp; wiſh that his were ſuch a people, that in ſo extreame &amp; deſperate a caſe, would for the ſafetie of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, labour what they coulde, in an orderlie proceeding the death of another? For ſince they haue but one head vnto whom they are ſworne; ſince they haue but one annointed whom God hath ſet ouer them: whoſoeuer he bee that ſeeketh by treacherie to bereaue their Soueraigne of his life, or by ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> force to trouble their eſtate; though he be a prince and annointed of the Lord, yet vnto them he is no prince, nor giuen of God to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them; but a ſtranger, and (as he by his own deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeines hath made himſelfe) an enemie. Wherefore ſince no good prince will accept him as his fellow &amp; equal, that is the ſecret co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triuer of another prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces death; ſince neceſſitie enforceth, and the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:8764:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>eſtate of princes otherwiſe requireth, that, which nature teacheth, reaſon vrgeth; God allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; the preſidents of princes, the aduiſe of popes; the cenſure of lawyers, the authoritie of the lawe (which is the moſt egall iudge) farther confirmeth and approueth: Let no man thinke ſtraunge that one prince may redeeme his ſaftie by the death of an other, <hi>Pereat Adonia, &amp; viuat Salomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The ſecond caſe.</head>
               <p>AND touching the ſecond point,<note place="margin">Lawfull for the king to draw his ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther king for the preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like peace.</note> as it is lawfull in a prince for the ſafetie of his life, which the other daily ſeeketh to deſtroy, to draw his ſworde againſt another; ſo much rather, when togeather with his owne perſon the good eſtate of his whole people &amp; common wealth is endangered: For this the prince is ſworne to preſerue vnto them in duty &amp; conſcience he is bound, theſe hee ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre before his owne life, or whatſoeuer is deareſt to him in the worlde. There is no ſuch bonds of friendſhip betwixt him and any other, no ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and loue to be ſhewed, but in regard of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, in regard of his people to him, they ought to be of farre leſſe account and value:<note place="margin">Tullie.</note> 
                  <hi>Nulla poteſt eſſe lex ſanctior quam rei publicaeſalus, nec vinculum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctius quam quod eſt patriae.</hi> For as this ſtandeth with the prince his honor to ſaue a prince that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be ſaued: ſo howe doth this ſtande with his honor, not to reſpect the future ſafetie of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? to ſaue a prince that is vnworthy to be ſaued, nay that is likely to be the verie ruine and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his countrie. So that if the caſe ſo ſtandeth, that he muſt needes allow the execution of ſome
<pb facs="tcp:8764:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>or by ſufferance be the cauſe of the ouerthrow of his countrie: he were impious to his countrie, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el to his people,<note place="margin">That is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les crueltie, that ſaueth one to the plague of many.</note> that would chooſe the ſafetie of one, with the ruine and deſtruction of manie, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the ſaftie of many thouſands of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the death of one, which deſerueth to die. And this appeareth more plaine in an Epiſtle of <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> to <hi>Boniface,</hi> and is canonized in the decrees,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus in Epiſt. ad Boniſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium cap. <hi>23.</hi> q. c. noli.</note> 
                  <hi>Sicut bellanti &amp; reſiſtenti violentia redditur, ita victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs cap to miſericordia iam debetur: maximè in quo pacis perturbatio non timetur.</hi> By which decree appeareth, that whereas any ſtir or trouble of the peace pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like is feared, there ſeuere iuſtice, and not remiſſe mercy is to be extended.</p>
               <p>So in this ſence the ſaide lawe hath beene in the like caſe of princes,<note place="margin">Hugolinus. Ioh. de lignano in tractaiu de bello.</note> namely in the caſe of king <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radine</hi> by <hi>Hugolinus,</hi> and other the beſt learned of their time, ruled and adiudged, as <hi>Ioh. de lignano</hi> reporteth, and not without great reaſon: for elſe to ſaue one particular perſon for pitie ſake,<note place="margin">The reaſon and Soule of the lawe.</note> and to ſhewe no ſparke of pitie to the whole realme, were no mercy at al, but a pitileſſe crueltie. For as S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>Sicut eſt miſericordia puniens, ita eſt crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas parcens</hi> as there is mercie in puniſhing,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus ad Marcellum.</note> ſo there is crueltie in ſparing: which by many preſidents of ſundry princes may be ſhowen.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Salomon</hi> (vnto whome for wiſedome no Prince was euer comparable) when he conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what was intended by his brother <hi>Adonia,</hi> (who yet thirſted and longed for his crowne) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a conſcience to endaunger the life of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, the which aſſuredly had followed, if either
<pb facs="tcp:8764:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Adonia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Regum. 2.</note> or any for him, had taken armes: without any farder proceſſe, hee commaunded him to be taken and ſlaine.</p>
               <p>So did the vertuous and moſt mercifull Empe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſebius, Mex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ia, &amp; alii.</note> vpon the like feare of a newe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and deſtruction of his people, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the life of the Emperour <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So did king <hi>Henrie</hi> the 5. after his glorious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie ouer the French at <hi>Egincourt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Grafton in his Cronicles on the raigne of H. 5.</note> ſhewe great clemencie vnto the perſons that were taken: but when his tentes were ſpoyled, and he iuſtly feared a newe aſſault: then contrarie to his accuſtomed pitie, he commaunded euerie man vpon paine of his life, to kill his priſoner: for then to haue ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, beginning a ſeconde fight might haue turned to the deſtruction of him &amp; his whole armie.</p>
               <p>And therefore leaſt a prince might ſeeme to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour one aboue the ſafetie of his people, and to leeſe the heartes of his loyall ſubiectes, by not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing care of them, and their poſteritie; leaſt the maſſacring of them be reputed his fault, and God require their bloud at his hand; leaſt by his conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie he ſhould embolden the hearts of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and cauſe his ſubiectes to take part with the enemie: hee may well conclude as in the like caſe did <hi>Cicero, Natura me clementem, ſed patria ſeuerum fecit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tullie contra Catelinam.</note> Nature made me pitifull, but the loue of my countrey hath made me cruell. <hi>Pereat Abſolon &amp; viuat Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herefore let all the world witneſſe, and the conſciences of good men, which without all partiall affection in the ſinglenes of their hearts, follow &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour a truth, what the Prince and people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for the glory of God, and furtherance of his truth, for the ſafegard of her Maieſtie and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their eſtate, either could or ſhould haue done rather than this; by the death of one trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, and treaſon-working perſon, to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed the quiet and ſafetie of themſelues.</p>
            <p>For ſince ſhee hath taken on her the armes and title of the crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and refuſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale her doings being thereunto ſollicited: ſince ſhe hath been the ruin of many worſhipfull hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and cauſe of the deſtruction of ſome of the Nobilitie.</p>
            <p>Since ſhe incited the rebels of the <hi>North</hi> to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie open warre againſt her Maieſtie; and releeued them being fled, by her friends in <hi>Scotland;</hi> &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by the Pope, who through her procurement ſent to their reliefe in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> 12000. crownes: Nay ſince, not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with al this, ſhe hath labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by her letters and miniſters, ſundry forreine princes to inuade this realme: &amp; the pope &amp; Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh king, with ſundry co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bined &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federed, haue a long time intended, in part haue practiſed, and are now in ſome readineſſe to performe the ſame.</p>
            <p>Since her feed ſeruaunt <hi>Morgan</hi> practiſed with <hi>Parrie</hi> to murder our Soueraigne, &amp; ſhee after ſhee knew it, yet fauoured &amp; maintained him ſtill.</p>
            <p>Since by her priuitie conſent and direction, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bington</hi> with his companie woulde haue killed her
<pb facs="tcp:8764:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>Maieſtie, &amp; ſhe promiſed to reward their doings in them, or if they miſcaried in their poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Let kings &amp; princes &amp; all nations of the earth witnes, whether euer ſo many, ſo mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous, ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible treaſons were committed by a prince, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and that againſt the Lords annointed, in her owne realme and if they were, yet that euer they eſcaped vnpuniſhed.</p>
            <p>And heere although ſo many impieties do call for vengeance and commaunde by Gods lawe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Magiſtrate to iuſtice ſo high a treſpaſſer: yet, ſee, vpon pitie rather than pollicie; hoping for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, rather than looking for a newe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie; not harkening to the manifold requeſtes of her humble, loyall, and moſt louing ſubiectes, her maieſtie continued her a troubleſome <hi>Ionas</hi> in the ſhippe of <hi>Englande</hi> ſtill: yet notwithſtanding after, ſince the graceleſſe mindes of maleconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſubiects, could not ſo be ſatiſfied, nor her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties great clemency could worke in them a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their dutie, but like nettles the gentler they were handled, the more they ſtinged.</p>
            <p>Since after her condempnation publiſhed, the Scottiſh Queenes fauorits, yet againe and againe, practiſed the death of her Maieſtie:</p>
            <p>Since the Pope for her ſake hath curſed our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine and his ſeedes men teach, that the Queene is no Queene, if the Pope depoſe her:</p>
            <p>Since they haue encouraged her euill minded ſubiectes, to moue rebellion, &amp; like vipers brood to gnaw out the wombe of our common mother:</p>
            <p>Since her fauourites concluded at home, that which was conſulted abroad, &amp; is of late confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them, to inuade our Realmes, ouerrun the
<pb facs="tcp:8764:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>lande, ſpoyle the Cities, maſſacre the ſubiectes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy her Maieſtie, and together with religion to make a change of the gouernment that is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, nay to ſubiect vs all, our goods, lands, liberties, children, poſteritie, to the ſlauerie and tyranny of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and forraine power.</p>
            <p>Since the whole Realme aſſembled in Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t made their many and humble petitions vnto her Maieſtie, as ſpecially interreſſed in the matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bodie of the ſame common wealth, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of her Maieſtie is the head, by taking away one to deliuer them all from their preſent feares &amp; future daungers. Sithens her Maieſtie was moued by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of her oth, than ſolemnely taken whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe was inueſted in her crown to diſtribute iuſtice equally to all, and to defende her Realme, &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, crowne, and dignitie, from the peſtilent vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners &amp; ſubuerters of the ſame; ſithens the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grew ſo daungerous, &amp; came to that extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that either her Maieſty muſt iuſtice &amp; ſentence the Scottiſh Queene, or muſt hazarde the loſſe of her life, the diſturbance of the common peace, the conqueſt of her countrey, the loſſe of the loue &amp; heartes of her ſubiectes, without which no Prince can well gouerne, or kingdome ſtande.</p>
            <p>Sithens the like ſentence and execution of life and death, as the Scottiſh Queene hath receiued is teſtified, confirmed and warranted by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, reaſons, &amp; examples of ſo many Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kinges, and Popes. Since no lawe will ſaue ſo high a treſpaſſer, but the law of Nations, of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of euery kingdome and countrey would inflict death on ſo great offenders.</p>
            <p>Sithens the like ſentence and execution haue
<pb facs="tcp:8764:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>been practiſed and put in vre by godly and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, and that vpon conſultation diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and reſolution of the cauſe by learned men of the lawe.</p>
            <p>Sithence the ſtatute lawe of euerie kingdome, where the intent of the lawe makers is ſuch, doth binde aſwell the king himſelfe as euery other king comming within &amp; offending in that iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Since the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> by her delict &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold offences, made herſelf ſo fubiect to the lawes of this countrey, as if ſhe had actually conſented to them.</p>
            <p>What man of reaſon, in whom there is any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall loue to his countrie or apparance of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man would not counſell by iuſtice to remoue the Scottiſh queen; the very plague &amp; calamity of our countrie, the very ground-worke &amp; chiefe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſiue cauſe of all theſe treaſons &amp; conſpiracies; the hope of diſconte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſubiects; &amp; the very cauſe, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope thundereth &amp; keepeth this ſtir, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo many monſters haue aduentured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to deſtroy her Maieſtie, &amp; for whoſe ſake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pretende to haue iuſt cauſe offered to inuade this land.</p>
            <p>To conclude, ſince that mercy is without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that ſpareth one to the ſpoile of ſo many; ſince to do iuſtice on the offender cannot be but hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, &amp; God is well pleaſed in the puniſhment of the wicked; ſince there was no hope of reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with one, which deadly hated, and was ſtill aſpiring to the preſent poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kingdome; ſince there was no remedie left, but to iuſtice her, or to liue in continuall feare of being daily murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>many attempting ſince her ſentence publiſhed to deſtroy her Maieſtie: Since many good princes haue redeemed their ſafeties with the death of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and there is no iuſt place or cauſe left to her of complaint, that is ſo dealt with, as ſhee woulde haue dealt with other.</p>
            <p>Let other princes and people of the earth make the queene of <hi>Englands</hi> caſe, their caſe &amp; the ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> the ſtate of their countrie: than I doubt not but as <hi>England</hi> hath done, ſo would they haue done: and as <hi>England</hi> is right ſorie, that ſuch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were committed, ſo would they ſorrow, if they eſcaped vnpuniſhed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <head type="sub">In the first chapter.</head>
            <p>IN the 3. page in margine, examinution, for examination. In the 5. pag. maintenatce, for maintenance. 6. pag. in marg. letters imploiment, for, letters of imploiment. Ibid. Petrus exea, for Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us Mexia. 8. pag. laly, for Italie. In the 2. Analogie, Firſt pag. by any writer, for by any good writer. Ibid. in margine, marentij, for maxentij. 2. pag. in marg colledge for collegue. 6. pag. in fine, to England, for of England. In the 3. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Sixt pag. that than poſteſted in the kingdome, for, that than were poſſeſſed in the kingdome. Ibid. pag. Conradine king, for Conrade king. priſoned, for, poyſoned. hee bequeathed, for, who bequeathed. Ione Neapolitan Queene, for, Ione the Neapolitan Queene. In the 4. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In marg. 2. pag. of putting a king to death, pro, for putting a king to death. In the 5. chapter, ſecond pag. preſciencie, for preſcience. Ibidem made in the ſame effect, for, to the ſame effect. 3. pag. than being kept cloſe priſoner, for, than this to bee kept a cloſe priſoner. 4. pag. an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence giuen in the higheſt degree, for, an offence committed in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree. 3. pag. therein, adding. without comma therein. in the time of Embaſsie, for in the time of their Embaſsie. In the 6. chapter. And is a law, for, it is a law. Fardinand Vaſkins, for, Vaſkius. to the 3. obiection, her priuie conſent, for, her priuitie, conſent, and promiſe. to the 4. obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, expreſſe accord, for, expreſſe action. In the 7. chapter. in vita Conradini, for, vita Conradini.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anthony Babingtons letter</hi> to the Queene of Scots.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST mighty, moſte excellent, my dread Soueraigne Lady and Queene, vnto whome<note n="a" place="margin">Onely obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Queene of Scots: <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgo</hi> not to the Queene of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</note> onely I doo owe all fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and obedience. It may pleaſe your gratious Maieſty to admit excuſe for my long ſilence and diſcontinuance from your due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull office, incepted vpon the remoue of your Royall perſon from the auncient place of your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boade, to the cuſtodie of a wicked puritane, a mortal enemy both by faith and faction to your Maieſty and ſtate Catholike, I held the hope of your countreyes<note n="b" place="margin">The weale of the realme to depend vpon the Queene of Scots.</note> weale (depending next vnder God vpon the life and health of your Maieſtie,) to bee deſperate, and thereupon reſolued to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the land, determining to ſpend the remna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my life in ſuch ſolitary ſort as the wretched &amp; miſerable eſtate of my countrey did require, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="c" place="margin">He expected the confuſion of the realme.</note> expecting according to the iuſt iudgement of God the deſerued confuſion thereof (which the Lord of his mercy ſake preuent:) the which my purpoſe beeing in execution and ſtanding vpon my departure, there was addreſſed vnto me from the parts beyonde the ſeas, one<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ballard</hi> the traitor comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ded for a man of vertue, and zealous to their religion &amp; the Squeens ſeruice.</note> 
               <hi>Ballard</hi> a man of vertue and learning, and of a ſingular zeale to the Catholike cauſe, and your Maieſties ſeruice, the
<pb facs="tcp:8764:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>man enformed mee of great preparation by the Chriſtian princes your Maieſties Allies for the deliuerance of our countrey,<note n="e" place="margin">Preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Chriſtian prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces her maieſt. allies of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine inuaſion for alteration of religion.</note> from the extreame and miſerable eſtate, wherein it hath ſo long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained. which when I vnderſtood, my ſpeciall deſire was, to aduiſe by what meanes I mighte with the hazard of my life and my freinds gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, to do your ſacred Maieſtie<note n="f" place="margin">One good daies ſeruice.</note> one good dayes ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Whereupon moſte dreade Soueraigne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the greate care, whiche thoſe princes haue of the preſeruation and ſafe deliuerance of your Maieſt. ſacred perſon, I aduiſed of meanes &amp; conſidered of circumſtances according to the weight of the affaires. And after long conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conference had with ſo many of your wiſeſt and moſt truſty,<note n="g" place="margin">The conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> as with ſafety I might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the ſecrecie thereof vnto: I do find (by the aſsiſtaunce of our Lord Ieſus) aſſurance of good effect &amp; deſired fruit of our trauel. Theſe things are firſt to be aduiſed in this great &amp; honorable action vpon the iſſue of which depends not onely the life of your moſt excellent Ma. (which GOD long preſerue to our moſt ineſtimable comfort &amp; the ſaluation of Engliſh ſoules,<note n="h" place="margin">Vpon theſe traiterous act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions depended 1. the life of the Sc. Qu. 2. thewealth of the countrey 3. reſtauration of faith. 4. redemption from hereſy.</note> &amp; the life of vs al actors heerin) but alſo the wealth of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey far then our liues more deere vnto vs, and the laſt hope euer to recouer the faith of our forefathers and to redeeme our ſelues from the ſeruitude &amp; bondage which hereſie hath impoſed vs, with the loſſe of a 1000 ſoules. Firſt aſſuring of inuaſion with ſufficient ſtrength in the inuadors partes to arriue well appointed with a ſtrong part at euery place to ioine with them &amp; warrant the landing,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>the deliuerance of your Ma. the diſpatch of the vſurped<note n="l" place="margin">He calleth our Queene an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titor.</note> competitor, for the<note n="m" place="margin">Theſe deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate practiſcs vndertaken by B.</note> effectuating of all which it may pleaſe your Excellency to rely vpon my ſeruice, I vow and I proteſt before the face of almighty god (who hath miraculouſly long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued your ſacred perſon no doubt toſome vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall good end) that what I haue ſaide ſhall bee<note n="o" place="margin">To be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or to dye.</note> perfourmed, or al our bodies happily loſt in the execution thereof, Which<note n="p" place="margin">The traitors vowe and oth taken.</note> vow all the cheif act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors heerein haue taken ſolemly, and are vpon aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance by your Maieſties letters vnto me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bleſſed ſacrament therupon, either to preuaile in the Churches behalf and your Maieſt. or fortunately to die for the honorable cauſe.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as the delay is extreame daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, it may pleaſe your Excellent Ma. by your wiſdome to direct vs, and by your princelye au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to enable ſuch as may aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the affairs foreſeeing that there is not any of the nobility at liberty, aſſured to your Maieſtie in this deſperate ſeruice (except vnknowne to vs.) And ſeeing it verye neceſſarye that ſome there bee to become heades to leade the multitude, euer diſpoſed by nature in this lande to followe<note n="q" place="margin">ſome noble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be head.</note> Nobilitye, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering withall it doeth not onelye make the commons and the countrey to followe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction or contention, which is euer founde in equalitye, but alſo doth adde greate courage to the<note n="r" place="margin">Addeth cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to the leaders.</note> leaders. For whiche neceſſarye regards I woulde recommend ſome to your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, as fitteſt in my knowledge to bee your Liuetenants in the Weſte parts, in the Northe parts, Southwales and Northwales, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Lancaſter Derbie and Stafford.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> All which countreyes by parties already made, &amp; fidelity taken in your Maieſties name, I holde vs moſt aſſured and of vndoubted fidelity. My ſelfe with 10.<note n="ſ" place="margin">The deliuery of the Queene of Scots.</note> gentlemen and an hundred followers will vndertake the deliuery of your royall perſon from the hands of your enemies, from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of the vſurped (from the obedience of whome, by the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her we are made free<note n="t" place="margin">Our Queenes death the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note>) There be 6. noble<note n="v" place="margin">The tragicall execution by 6 gentlemen.</note> Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al my priuat freinds who for the zeale they beare to the Catholique cauſe, and your Maieſties ſeruice, wil vndertake that tragicall execution. It reſteth according to their infinit good deſerts &amp; your maieſties boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie their honorable attempt may be honorably<note n="x" place="margin">Ambition &amp; aſpiring hope.</note> rewarded in them (if they eſcape with life) or in their poſteritie, and that ſo much I may be able by your Maieſties authority to aſſure them. Now it remaineth onely, that by your Maieſties wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it be reduced into<note n="y" place="margin">The S. queen to preſcribe the method of theſetraiterous actions.</note> method, that your happy deliuerance be firſt, for that therevppon dependeth the onelye good, and that all other circumſtances ſo concurre that the vntimelie fall of one end doe not ouerthrow the reſt. Al which your Maieſties wonderfull experience and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome will diſpoſe of in ſo good manner, as I doubt not through Gods aſsiſtance all ſhal come to deſired effect. For the obteyning of which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of vs ſhall thinke his life moſt happilye ſpent. Vpon the 12. day of this moneth I wil be at <hi>Leichfield</hi> expecting your Maieſties aunſwere &amp; letters, in readineſſe to execute what by them ſhalbe commaunded.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt faithfull ſubiect, and ſworne ſeruaunt</hi> Anthony Babinton</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Queene of Scots letter to <hi>Anthony Babington. xij. Iuly.</hi> 1586.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruſty and welbeloued. According to the zeale and entire affection which I haue known in you towards the<note n="a" place="margin">Two things in tended. 1 rehgion 2 her cauſe.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cauſe of religion and<note n="b" place="margin">Her cauſe 1 for her deli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery 2 bringing in of forraine forces 3 the murdring of the Qu. ma. 4 Rebellion within the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme.</note> mine: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alwayes made account of you, as a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and right worthy member to be imployed both in the one and the other: It hath beene no leſſe conſolation vnto me, to vnderſtand your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as I haue doone by your laſte, and to haue founde meanes to renue myne intelligence with you; than I felt greife all this while paſte, to bee without the fame. I pray you therefore fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth to write vnto me ſo often as you can of all occurrances which you may iudge in any wiſe important to the good of my affaires. Wherunto I ſhall not faile to correſponde with all the care &amp; diligence that ſhalbe in my poſsibility. For di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers great and important conſiderations which were heere too long to be deduced, I cannot but greatly praiſe and commend your common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to preuent in time the deſſeignment of our enemies for the extirpation of our religion out of this realme, with the ruine of vs all. For I haue long<note n="c" place="margin">Pretenſes long ſithence with o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther princes for alteration of religion heere.</note> ago ſhewen vnto the forraine Catholike princes, and experience doth approue it, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that they and we<note n="d" place="margin">by delay of execution of the complotts the number of Papiſts dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</note> delay to put helping hand on the matter on this ſide, the greater leaſure haue our ſaid enemies to preuaile and winne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage ouer the ſaid princes, as they haue done againſt the king of Spaine. And in the meane
<pb facs="tcp:8764:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>time the Catholiques heere remaining expoſed to all kinde of perſecution and crueltie, do day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diminiſh in number, forces, meanes, &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. So as if remedie bee not thereunto haſtelye prouided, I feare not a little, but that they ſhal become altogether vnable for ener to ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and to receaue any aid at all, whenſoeuer it were offered them. For mine owne parte I pray you to aſſure our principall freindes, that albeit I had not in this cauſe anye particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt (that which I may pretend vnto beeing of no conſideration vnto me in reſpect of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good of this ſtate) I ſhalbe alwayes ready and moſte willing to imploye therein my life and all that I haue, or may euer looke for in this worlde. Now for to ground ſubſtantially this enetrpriſe, and to bring it to good ſucceſſe, you muſte firſte examine deepely what<note n="e" place="margin">Forces of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teins to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in euery ſhire in englad</note> forces aſwell on foote as on horſe, you may raiſe amongeſt you all, and what captaines you ſhall appoint for them in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſhire, in caſe a cheife generall cannot bee had. Of what townes,<note n="f" place="margin">Ports and hauens to bee aſſured for landing.</note> Portes, and hauens you maye aſſure your ſelues of, aſwell in the North, Weſte, as Southe, to receaue<note n="g" place="margin">Succour from France, Spaine and the lowe untr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yes.</note> ſuccour. from the Lowe Countreyes, Spaine, and France What<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>co be place fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to aſſemble their forces</note> place you eſteeme fitteſt and of greateſt, aduauntage to aſſemble the principall company of your forces at, and the ſame beeing aſſembled whiche way you haue to march. What<note n="i" place="margin">What forraine forces woulde be required</note> forren forces aſwell on horſe as foote, you require, whiche woulde bee compaſſed conforme to the proportion of yours) for how long paie &amp; what<note n="k" place="margin">What proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, money &amp;c</note> munition and ports the fitteſt for their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in this realme, from the three foreſaide for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren
<pb facs="tcp:8764:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>Countreyes. What prouiſion of money and armour (in caſe you want) you woulde aske. By what meanes doe the ſix<note n="l" place="margin">The 6. gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> Gentlemen deliberate to proceede.<note n="m" place="margin">Her owne deliuerance.</note> And the manner alſo of my get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of this holde vpon which pointes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken amongeſt you (who are the principall authours, and alſo as few in number as you can) the beſt reſolution, my aduife is that you imparte the ſame with all diligence, to <hi>Bernardino de Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">To impart all to Bernardine de Mendoza</note> Ambaſſador Leiger for the king of Spayne in Fraunce, who beſide the experience hee hath of the ſtate of this ſide, I may<note n="o" place="margin">Her aſſurance of the ſpaniſhe ambaſſadour.</note> aſſure you will imploye himſelfe moſt willinglye. I ſhall not faile to write vnto him of the matter with all the earneſt recommendations that I can, as I ſhall alſo to any elſe that ſhalbe needfull.</p>
            <p>But you muſt make choyſe for managing of this affaire with the ſaide Mendoza and others out of the realme, of ſome faithfull and verye ſecreat perſonage, vnto whome onelye you muſte commit your ſelues, to the end thinges bee kept more ſecreat, whiche for your owne ſecuritye I commend vnto you aboue the reſt. If your Meſſenger bring you backe againe ſure promiſe and ſufficient aſſurance of the ſuccour which you demaunde, then thereafter (but no ſooner for that it were in vaine) take diligent order that all theſe of your partie on this ſide, make ſo ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye as they can, prouiſion of armour, fitte horſe and ready money, wherewith to hold themſelues in<note n="p" place="margin">Readines for to marche</note> readineſſe to march ſo ſoone, as it ſhall bee ſignified vnto them by their chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals in euery ſhire.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And for better<note n="q" place="margin">The colour in prouiding armour and horſe to be the papiſts defence againſt the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titans.</note> colouring of the matter (refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the principals the knowledge of the ground of the enterpriſe) it ſhalbe inough for the beginning to giue out to the reſte, that the ſaide prouiſions are made onelye for fortifiing your ſelues in caſe of neede againſte the puritans of this realme. The principall whereof hauing the chiefe forces of the ſame in the lowe countreyes, haue (as you may let the bruit go) deſſeigned to<note n="r" place="margin">A ſlaunderous rumor of a maſſacre.</note> ruine and ouerthrow at their returne home, the whole Catholikes, and to vſurpe the crowne not onely againſt mee and all the lawfull pretenders thereunto: but againſt their owne Queene, that now is, if ſhe will not altogither commit her ſelfe to their onelye gouernment. The ſame pretexte may ſerue to founde and eſtabliſh amongeſt you all an<note n="ſ" place="margin">A wicked aſſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciation</note> aſſociation and conſideration generall, as done onely for your owne iuſt preſeruations and defence aſwell in the religion, as liues, lands and goods againſt the attempts of the ſaide puritans, without touching directly by writing any thing againſt the Queene. But rather<note n="t" place="margin">An old pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of rebels to pretend one thing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend another.</note> ſhewing your ſelues willing to maintaine her and her lawfull heirs after her not naming me. The affaires bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus prepared, and forces in readineſſe both without and within the realme, then ſhall it bee time to ſet the<note n="v" place="margin">The 6. gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men toexecute the deſſeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> ſix gentlemen to worke, taking order vpon the accompliſhing of their diſſeigne, I may be ſuddainly tranſported out of this place, and that al your forces in the ſame time be on the field to meete mee in tarying for the arriuall of forren aide, which then muſt be haſtened with al diligence. Now for that there can be no certaine day appoynted of the accompliſhing of the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:8764:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>gentlemens deſſeignement, to the ende that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be in readines to take me from hence I would that the ſaide gentlemen had alwayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, or at the leaſt at court,<note place="margin">Some to bee furniſhed with ſpeedy horſe to aduertiſe the deſſeigne</note> a fower ſtout men furniſhed with good and ſpeedie horſes, for ſo ſoone as the ſaid deſſeigne ſhall bee executed, to come with all diligence to aduertiſe thereof thoſe that ſhalbe appointed for my tranſporting to the end that immediatly thereafter, they may be at the place of my aboade before that my ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per can haue aduiſe of the execution of the ſayde deſſeigne, or at leaſt before he can fortifie hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe within the houſe, or carrye mee out of the ſame. It were neceſſary to diſpatch two or three of the ſaide aduertiſers by diuerſe wayes, to the ende that if one bee ſtayed, the other may come through: and at the ſame inſtant were it alſo needfull to aſſaye to cut of the poſtes ordinarye wayes. This is the plotte whiche I find beſt for this enterpriſe, and the order wherby you ſhould conduct the ſame for our commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecurities. For ſturring on this ſide before you be well<note n="y" place="margin">To be ſure of forren forces before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion begin heere.</note> aſſured of ſufficient forre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forces, it were but for nothing to put your ſelues in daunger of following the miſerable fortune of ſuch as haue hertofore tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled in like occaſions. And to take mee out of this place vnbeeing before<note n="z" place="margin">Vpon her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery to ſet he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r in the middeſt of an army of rebels.</note> well aſſured to ſette me in the middeſt of a good army, or in ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good ſtrength, where I may ſafelie ſtaie on the aſſembly of your forces, and arriuall of the ſaide forren ſuccours, it were ſufficient cauſe geuen to that Queene in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> catching me againe, to incloſe mee for euer in ſome hole, forth of the which I ſhould neuer eſcape, if ſhe did vſe mee no worſe,
<pb facs="tcp:8764:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>and to purſue with all extremitie thoſe that had aſsiſted me, which would grieue me more than al the vnhap which might befall on my ſelfe. And therefore muſt I needs yet once againe admoniſh you ſo earneſtly as I can, to looke and take heede moſt carefully and vigilantly to compaſſe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſo well all that ſhall be neceſſarie for the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuating of the ſaide enterpriſe,<note n="2" place="margin">She referreth the managing of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plot to the domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call traitors.</note> as with the grace of God you may bring the ſame to happie ende, remitting to the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our principal friends on this ſide with whom you haue to deale there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to ordein or conclude vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this preſent (which ſhall ſerue you onely for an ouerture and propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition) as you ſhall among you finde beſt. And to your ſelfe in particular I referre to<note n="3" place="margin">The reward promiſed to the 6. gentlemen.</note> aſſure the gentlemen aboue mentioned of all that ſhall be requiſite on my part for the entire execution of their goodwill, I leaue alſo to your common<note n="4" place="margin">The reſt of the enterpriſe referred to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideration, if the deſſeigne were not done.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions (in caſe the deſſeignment doe not take holde as may happen) whether you will or not purſue my tranſport and the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the reſt of the enterpriſe. But if the miſhappe ſhould fall out, that you ſhould not come by me being ſet in the Tower of London, or in anye other ſtrength with great gard,<note n="5" place="margin">But if ſhe were kept in the tower that then for Gods ſake the reſt of the conſpiracie muſt proceede.</note> yet notwithſtanding leaue not for Gods ſake to proceede in the reſt of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, for I ſhall at anie time die moſt conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnderſtanding of your deliuerie foorth of the<note n="6" place="margin">Our freedom vnder our moſt gratious Qu. ſhe calleth a ſeruitude and ſlauerie.</note> ſeruitude, wherein you are holden as ſlaues. I ſhall aſſaye at the ſame time that the woorke ſhalbe in hande in theſe partes, to make the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques of<note n="7" place="margin">She would raiſe a rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Scotland and take the king her ſonne priſoner.</note> 
               <hi>Scotlande</hi> to ariſe, and to put my ſonne in their hands to the effect that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence our enemies here may not preuaile of any ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.
<pb facs="tcp:8764:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>I woulde alſo that ſome<note n="8" place="margin">A rebellion or inuaſion in lielande.</note> ſtirring in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande were laboured for, and to beginne ſome while before that any thing were doone here, to the ende that the alarum might be giuen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by on the<note n="9" place="margin">But the blow and inuaſion to come by the king of Spains forces, out of Flaunders.</note> flatte contrarie ſide that the ſtroke ſhould come from. Your reaſons to haue ſome generall<note n="10" place="margin">She liked to haue an head and chiefe ſtaie in rebellion.</note> heade or chiefe me thinkes are verye pertinent, and therefore were it good to ſounde ſome obſcurely for that purpoſe. From ouer ſea the<note place="margin">11|The Earle of Weſtmerland a man of that faction.</note> Earle of Weſtmerlande may bee had, whoſe houſe and name may doe muche, you knowe, in the North partes, as alſo the<note n="12" place="margin">The L. Paget to returne and be head of the conſpiracie.</note> Lorde Paget of good abilitie in ſome ſhieres here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts. Both the one and the other may bee brought home ſecretly: amongeſt whome ſome moe of the principall baniſhed may returne, if the enterpriſe be once reſolute. The ſayde Lord Paget is nowe in Spaine and may intreate all there, which by his brother<note n="13" place="margin">Charles Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.</note> 
               <hi>Charles</hi> you will commit vnto him, touching this affaire. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that none of your meſſengers, whome you ſende forth of the Realme,<note n="14" place="margin">A caueat for tranſporting of letters.</note> carrie ouer any let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vpon themſelues, but make their diſpatch be conueied eyther after or before them by ſome other: take good heede of ſpies and<note n="15" place="margin">A caueat of falſe brethren and eſpecially prieſtes.</note> falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that are amongeſt you, ſpecially by ſome Prieſts that are alreadie by our enemies wrought for your diſcouerie. And in anye wiſe neuer keepe anye<note n="16" place="margin">A caueat to keepe no paper that may doe harme.</note> paper about you that may in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorte doe harme, For from like<note n="17" place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience that hath happened by papers.</note> errors haue come the onely condemnation of all ſuche as haue ſuffered heeretofore, againſt whome could there otherwiſe haue beene nothing prooued.
<pb facs="tcp:8764:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>Diſcouer as little as you can your names and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to the french Ambaſſadour now leiger in London, for although he be as I vnderſtand a very honeſt gentleman and of a good conſcience and religion, yet feare I that his Maiſter entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with that Queene, a courſe far contrarye to our deſſeignements, which may moue him to croſſe vs, if it ſhould happen he ſhould haue anye particular knowledge thereof, All this while paſt I haue ſued to change &amp; remoue from this houſe and for aunſwere onely the caſtle of Dudleye hath beene named to ſerue the tourne, ſo as by apperance within the end of this ſommer, I may go thither, Wherefore aduiſe ſo ſoone as I ſhall be there,<note place="margin">To make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſion for her eſcape when ſhe ſhal come to Dudley caſtle.</note> what prouiſion might bee had aboute that part 19 for my eſcape from thence. If I ſtaie heere, there is for that purpoſe one of theſe 20 three meanes following to be looked for, The firſte that at one certaine daye appointed in my walking abroade on horſebacke on the moores betwixt this and Stafford where ordinarilye you knowe very fewe people do paſſe,<note place="margin">Shee deuiſeth 3 meanes to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. The 1. meane to eſcape.</note> a fifty or three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore men well horſed and armed may come to take me there, as they may eaſily, my keeper ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing with him ordinarily but eighteene or twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty horſemen only with daggs. The ſecond meane to come at midnight or ſoone after to ſet fire in the barnes and ſtables which you know are neere to the houſe,<note place="margin">The ſecond.</note> and whileſt my Guardian his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts ſhall runne forth to the fire, your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hauing euery one a marke, whereby they may know one an other vnder night, might ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe the houſe, where I hope with the fewe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts I haue about mee, to giue you correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency.
<pb facs="tcp:8764:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>And the third, ſome that bring carts hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ordinarily comming early in the morning,<note place="margin">The 3 meane.</note> the carts might be ſo prepared, and with ſuche cart-leaders, that beeing iuſt in the middeſt of the great gate, the carts might fall downe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer whelme, and that therupon you might come ſodainly with your followers to make your ſelfe Maiſter of the houſe, and carry mee away, ſo you might doe eaſily before that any number of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diars (who lodge in ſundry places forth of this place, ſome half a mile, ſome a whole mile of) might come to their reliefe.<note place="margin">Her large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of reward to the traitors.</note> Whatſoeuer iſſue the matter take, I do and will think my ſelfe obliged as long as I liue towardes you for the offers you make to hazard your ſelfe as you doe for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery: And by any meanes that euer I may haue I ſhall do my endeuour to recognize by effect your deſerts heerin I haue commanded a more ample alphabet to be made for you, which herewith you ſhall receaue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The contents of a letter written by the Scottiſh Queene to <hi>Bernardin de Mendoza</hi> 20. of May, 1586. <hi>after the Popes Calender.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Finde my ſelfe greatly troubled what courſe to take<note n="a" place="margin">To take a new courſe for an other courſe before.</note> a newe for the affaires on this ſide the ſea: <hi>Charles Paget</hi> hath a charge from me to imparte vnto you certaine<note n="b" place="margin">an ouerture to be imparted to the ſpaniſh Ambaſſador for his maiſter by C. Paget.</note> ouertures in my behalfe: whereupon I pray you deliuer him freely, what you thinke may be obteyned thereof from the king your maiſter.</p>
            <p>There is an other point depending thereof, which I haue reſerued to write to your owne ſelfe for to bee by you ſent vnto the king your maiſter on my behalfe, no man elſe, if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, being priuie thereunto, that is, that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering my ſonnes great obſtinacie in hereſie, and foreſeeing hereupon the imminent daunger and harme like to enſue to the catholike church, hee comming to the ſucceſſion of this Realm: I haue reſolued with my ſelfe, in caſe my ſayde ſonne doe not reduce himſelfe before my death to the catholike religion (as I muſt tell you plainely, I haue ſmall hope ſo long as hee ſhall remaine in Scotlande) to<note n="c" place="margin">A promiſe to giue by her laſt will to the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh king the ſucceſsion of the crowne of England.</note> giue and graunt my right to the ſayde king your maiſter in the ſucceſsion of this crowne by my laſt will and teſtament, praying him in<note n="d" place="margin">Note the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</note> conſideration hereof from this time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to take me wholely into his protection, likewiſe the ſtate and affaires of this countrey, the which for diſcharge of my conſcience, I can not thinke I can put into the handes of a Prince
<pb facs="tcp:8764:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>more zealous of our religion and able in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes to reeſtabliſh the ſame on this ſide, as it importes all the reſt of Chriſtendome. Let this be kept<note n="e" place="margin">ſecreſie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for 3. cauſes 1. loſſe of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. 2. breach with her ſonne. 3. her totall ruyne.</note> ſecrete for as much as if it come to be reuealed, it ſhould be in Fraunce the loſſe of my dower, in Scotlande a cleare breach with my ſonne, and in this countrey my totall ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Thanke on my behalfe the ſayde kinge your maiſter for the fauour and liberalitie extended to the<note n="f" place="margin">The kinges li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie to the L. Paget and his brother.</note> L. <hi>Paget</hi> and his brother, which I praye him moſt earneſtly to continue, and to gratifie for my ſake with ſome pention<note n="g" place="margin">What poore Morgan hath endured for her and the common cauſe</note> poore <hi>Morgan,</hi> who hath ſo much endured not onely for me, but for the common cauſe.</p>
            <p>I recommende likewiſe vnto you,<note n="h" place="margin">Fulſambe to haue ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie.</note> 
               <hi>Fulſambe</hi> (whome you knowe) to helpe him to ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, aboue the entertainement, that I haue alotted him, according to the ſmall meanes I haue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Points out of <hi>Babingtons</hi> letter <hi>ſubſcribed by Curle.</hi> 13. <hi>Sep.</hi> 1586.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Vpon the ſight and peruſall of the copye of the letter written by Babington to the Queenes Maieſtie my miſtreſſe, I doe remember well that the clauſes heereafter written were conteined in the ſame let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpatched at her Maieſties commaundement by me Gilbert Curle <hi>23.</hi> of September. <hi>1586.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THere was addreſſed vnto me from the partes beyonde the ſeas one <hi>Ballard</hi> a man of vertue and learning, and of ſinguler zeale to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike cauſe and your Maieſties ſeruice. This man enformed me of great preparation by the Chriſtian princes your Maieſties alies for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance of our countrey from the extreame &amp; miſerable eſtate, wherein it hath ſo long remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: my eſpeciall deſire was to aduiſe by what meanes with the hazard of my life &amp; my freinds in generall, I might do your ſacred Maieſtie one good dayes ſeruice &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="continuation">
               <head>Afterwards did follow.</head>
               <p>THeſe things are firſt to be aduiſed in this great and honourable action &amp;c. Firſt, aſſuring of inuaſion: Sufficient ſtrength in the inuador, ports to arriue at, appointed with a ſtrong partye to ioyne with them, and warrant their landing. The deliuerance of her Maieſtie. The diſpatch of the vſurped competitor. For the effectuating of all which I vowe and proteſt &amp;c. that what I haue
<pb facs="tcp:8764:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaid ſhalbe performed, or all our liues happilye loſt in the execution thereof, which vowe all the chiefe actors haue taken ſolemnely, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="continuation">
               <head>After ſome other ſentences this doth follow.</head>
               <p>MY ſelfe with ten Gentlemen &amp; an hundreth our followers, wil vndertake the deliuerance of your Royall perſon from the handes of your enemies, for the diſpatch of the vſurper, from the obedience of whome (by the excommunication of her) we are made free: there be ſix noble gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen all my priuate freindes, who for the zeale they beare to the Catholike cauſe, and your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ſeruice, will vndertake the tragicall execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: It reſteth that according to their infinite good deſerts and your Maieſtics bountye, their heroicall attempt may bee honorablye rewarded in them, if they eſcape with life, or in their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and that ſo much I may be able by your Maieſties authority to aſſure them. &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>By me Gylbert Curle,</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <date>23. <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember.</hi> 1586.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="affirmation">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Nawes affirmation of the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Scottiſh Queenes writing</hi> tranſlated, out of her ciphered letters, 6. <hi>September.</hi> 1586.</head>
            <p>TOuching the letter written by the Queene of Scottes my Miſtres to Babington, I wrote the ſame by her expreſſe direction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, as I haue depoſed it. Touching the other letters (as alwaies her Maieſty hath accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med her ſelfe ſitting at table, and Curle and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her) her Maieſtie commaunded me particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and from point to point all that whiche it pleaſed her to haue written, and vnder her I did draw the points thereof as particularly, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply as may be. After I ſhewed and reade them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her according to the which (there reſting no more but the diſpoſition of the matter) I wrote the ſaid letters: and ſhewed them vnto her, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered the ſame, after which that was done ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with which it pleaſeth her Maieſtie to appoint, for her Maieſtie will not ſuffer that any do write her letters of ſecreſie, or importance out of her own Cabonet. And there is not any diſpatche ſealed, but that ſhe is preſent at it: And ſhe doth alwaies peruſe all the letters before they be put in Cipher and tranſlated, which is done by Curle, namely of the letter written to Babington.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:8764:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Pointes out of the Scottiſh <hi>Queenes letters ſubſcribed by Curle</hi> 23. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1586.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Certaine principall pointes conteined in the letter written from the Queene of Scottes in aunſwere to a letter of <hi>Babingtons,</hi> which were expreſsed by the ſaide Queene in theſe kinde of ſentences hereafter following, as vpon the ſight and peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the coppie of the letter which was firſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Nawe</hi> in French by the Queenes comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement I doe acknowledge to haue beene ſo writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>NOwe for to grounde ſubſtantially this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and to bring it to good ſucceſſe, you muſt firſt examine deepely what forces as wel on foote as on horſe, you may rayſe amongeſt you all, and what Captaines you ſhall appoint for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in euerie ſhire, in caſe a chiefe generall cannot be had. Of which townes, portes, and hauens you may aſſure your ſelfe, as well in the North, Weſt, as South, to receaue ſuccors from the Lowe countreyes, Spaine, and Fraunce. What places you eſteeme fitteſt and of greateſt aduantage, to aſſemble the principall companie of your forces and the ſame beeing aſſembled, which way you haue to march, what forrein forces you require, for howe long paie, &amp;c. what prouiſion of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, in caſe you want would you aske, by what meanes doe the vj. gentlemen deliberate to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, and the manner alſo of my getting foorth of this holde.</p>
            <div type="continuation">
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>In an other part of the ſame letter this alſo did followe.</head>
               <p>IF your meſſenger bring you backe againe ſure promiſe and ſufficient aſſurance of the ſuccour you demaunde, then thereafter, (but no ſooner, for that it were in vaine) take diligent order that all thoſe on your party on this ſide make ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly as they can, prouiſion of armour, fit horſe, and readie money, wherewith to holde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in readines to march, ſo ſoone as it ſhall be ſignified vnto them by their chiefe &amp; principales in euerie ſhire. And for better colouring of the matter reſeruing to the principall the knowledge of the ground of the enterpriſe, it ſhalbe enough for the beginning to giue out to the reſt, that the ſaide prouiſions are made onely for fortifying your ſelues in caſe of neede againſt the puritans of this Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="continuation">
               <head>In an other part of this ſame letter this alſo followeth.</head>
               <p>THe affaires beeing thus prepared and forces in readineſſe both without and within the Realme, than ſhall it bee time to ſet the ſix gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen to worke, taking order vpon the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of their deſſeignement, I may bee ſuddainly tranſported out of this place, and that all your forces in the ſame time be in the fielde to meete me tarying for the arriuall of forrain aide, which then muſt bee haſtened with all diligence. Nowe for that there can bee no certaine day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the accompliſhing of the ſaide Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemens
<pb facs="tcp:8764:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſſeignement, to the ende they may be in readineſſe to take me from hence: I woulde that the ſaid gentlemen had alwayes about them or at the leaſt at the Courte a fower ſtoute men, furniſhed with good and ſpeedy horſes, for, ſo ſoone as the ſaid deſſeigne ſhall bee executed, to come with al diligence to aduertiſe thereof, thoſe that ſhal be appointed for my tranſporting, to the ende that immediatly thereafter they may be at the place of my aboade before that my kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per can haue aduiſe of the execution of the ſaide deſſeignement, or at the leaſt before he can forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie himſelfe within the houſe or carry mee out of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="continuation">
               <head>It followeth alſo in the ſame letter.</head>
               <p>This is the plot which I finde beſt for this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and order whereby you ſhould conduct the ſame for our common ſecurity, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="continuation">
               <head>There followeth alſo in the ſame letter.</head>
               <p>I ſhall affaie, at the ſame time that the worke ſhall be in hand in theſe parts, to make the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques of Scotland to ariſe, and to put my ſonne into their hands, to the effecte that from thence our enemies heere may not preuaile of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuccour. I would alſo that ſome ſturring in Ireland were laboured for, and to beginne ſome while before that any thing were done heere, to to the end, the alarme might be giuen thereby on the flat contrary ſide that the blowe ſhould come from.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="continuation">
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Towards the ende of the Letter this doth followe.</head>
               <p>IF I ſtaie heere, there is for that purpoſe but one of theſe three meanes following. The firſt that on a certaine day appointed in my walking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade on horſeback on the mores betwixt this and Stafford, &amp;c. a fiftie or threeſcore men well horſed &amp; armed may come to take me there &amp;c. The ſeconde meane is to come at midnight or foone after to ſet fire on the barnes and ſtables which you knowe are neere to the houſe, and whileſt my guardiant ſeruaunts ſhall come forth to the fire, your companye might ſurpriſe the houſe &amp;c. And the thirde, ſome that bring carts hither ordinarily, their carts might bee ſo prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and with ſuch cart-leaders that beeing iuſte in the middeſt of the great gate, the carts might fall downe or ouerwhelme, and thereupon you might come ſuddainly with your followers, and make your ſelues maiſters of the houſe and carie me away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are the pointes that were in the letter written in the Queenes Maieſtie my Mistreſſe name to Babington, which as alreadie I haue ſaide and written, was firſt written in French by Maiſter Nawe, and tranſlated into Engliſh and ciphered by me Gilbert Curle by the Queenes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Septemb.</hi> 23. 1586.</p>
               <p>Navve in effect is conteſt vvith Curle, vvith the concurrency of Babington and Ballardes confeſsion, and other of the conſpiracie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8764:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
